中文字幕
This is CS50, and this is week 1.
And by the end of the day, you will know how
中文字幕
to create programs that look like this.
So this, of course, is binary.
中文字幕
This is the only language that machines ultimately understand.
But thankfully, per last week, there's so many abstractions
中文字幕
and there are so many humans that have come before us that we don't actually
have to write anything at this level.
中文字幕
We can abstract way above it like we did with Scratch already
and like we will starting today with C.
中文字幕
But does anyone nonetheless want to take a guess
at what that program, when fed to your Mac or PC, actually does?
中文字幕
Anyone recognize?
Anyone want to hazard a guess?
中文字幕
It's perhaps the simplest program you could write.
Indeed, it does, when fed to the brain of your computer,
中文字幕
the so-called CPU simply prints that.
So how do we actually get to that point?
中文字幕
Well, recall where we started this conversation last time
talking about computer science more generally
中文字幕
and problem solving-- we proposed could be distilled really is this.
You've got some inputs.
中文字幕
You want some outputs.
And somewhere in the middle, you need to do something with those inputs.
中文字幕
And to get to that point, though, we had to represent those inputs and outputs.
We just had to decide as humans, how are we going to represent all of the inputs
中文字幕
to our problem when it comes time to have a computer actually process them.
And at the end of the day, all of the phones and the computers that we're all
中文字幕
using only at the end of the day plug into the wall
to get their physical resource, electricity,
中文字幕
and they might store that temporarily in a battery.
But that really is our only input.
中文字幕
It's either plugged in or it's not.
It's either a 1 or a 0, true or false.
中文字幕
So the world really reduces to those two states, so to speak.
And so you can think of those states then as just being like a light bulb,
中文字幕
on or off.
I pulled up my cell phone last time to turn the flashlight on or off,
中文字幕
1 or 0, true or false.
Now of course, if you only have one light bulb,
中文字幕
you can only count from 0 to 1.
But if you start to have a bunch of them back to back to back to back,
中文字幕
you can permute them like I did my finger--
0, 1, 2, 3, and so forth.
中文字幕
And so we started talking about binary more generally.
And so here for instance were three sequences
中文字幕
of 0's and 1's and each of those represented something,
but we don't need to think about the world at that level.
中文字幕
We can abstract on top of that.
All of us are so much more familiar with decimal of course,
中文字幕
and indeed recall that this was just 72, 73, and 33, which if anyone recalls,
when you use ASCII--
中文字幕
which is this global standard for mapping numbers
to letters-- we got what message?
中文字幕
Yeah, it was just high, capital H capital I exclamation point.
And so that's an abstraction on top of those otherwise binary numbers.
中文字幕
But we don't have to model just text using numbers.
At the end of the day, our only resource is still that electricity,
中文字幕
and the only way we think about it digitally is still zeros and ones.
But if we take the same value--
中文字幕
72, 73, 33-- and treat them in the context of Photoshop
or a photo program or a graphics program,
中文字幕
we can instead interpret them as like some amount
of red, some amount of green, some amount of blue,
中文字幕
which gave us last time, recall, this yellowish color.
So now we had another abstraction on top of binary colors,
中文字幕
and this is just one pixel.
What can you do once you have more than one pixel?
中文字幕
What can you represent next?
Yeah, right, images.
中文字幕
So we're continuing the conversation up and up and up,
and we could represents something like a graphical emoji on the screen, which
中文字幕
has more than just one yellow dot.
It's got a whole bunch of yellow dots and other colors as well.
中文字幕
And recall that, if we want to animate things,
whether it's through silly things like animojis on a phone or just more proper
中文字幕
videos and movies, well, those are just sequences
of images flying past your human eyes really quite quickly.
中文字幕
So that's where we kind of left off last time starting at the base level
and abstracting away so that we could stipulate thereafter we
中文字幕
can represent inputs, and we can represent
outputs, whatever those happen to be.
中文字幕
And here on out, we don't need to think at that level.
We can just assume we all know how to do this.
中文字幕
And even if it eventually becomes kind of a distant memory,
we know that someone can indeed do this.
中文字幕
And that's the value of abstraction.
But inside of this black box are so-called algorithms,
中文字幕
the secret sauce--
this is where the problems are actually solved.
中文字幕
And we not only talked about what these algorithms are, but for instance,
how efficient they were.
中文字幕
So recall that this red line represented a very simple algorithm just turning
the phone book page by page one at a time.
中文字幕
And the reason that it's a straight line is because there's a one to one
correspondence between how many pages there are in the book
中文字幕
and how many page turns there are-- one page, one more page, one more
turn, and so forth.
中文字幕
If I fly through it at twice the speed--
2, 4, 6, 8--
中文字幕
I can do better.
And so that yellow line now, recall, was lower on the graph.
中文字幕
If you just look at any two points, yellow and red,
yellow is below red, saying it takes less time.
中文字幕
But it was not quite correct.
There was one bug when I was looking for Mike two pages at a time.
中文字幕
What was that issue?
Yeah, I might miss him.
中文字幕
He might accidentally get sandwiched in between two pages-- not a huge deal
because I could fix it, but I have to fix it.
中文字幕
I have to apply that additional logic and double back
at least a page if I go too fast.
中文字幕
But of course the final algorithm-- and frankly all of our initial intuition
probably-- was the dividing and conquer, open it roughly to the middle,
中文字幕
look down, and then go left, and go right,
and just repeat that process as the problem gets
中文字幕
this big to this big to this big to this big to just one page left.
So that was all about efficiency.
中文字幕
But to get to that point we needed to express ourselves more precisely.
And so we introduced pseudo code.
中文字幕
There's no formal definition.
It can be English, English like.
中文字幕
It's just meant to be succinct and get the point across.
And recall that, along the way, we introduced a whole bunch of concepts,
中文字幕
many of which you probably experimented with Scratch, like loops
and conditions, Boolean expressions, variables, and so forth.
中文字幕
And those were building blocks that came out of this kind of demonstration here.
But honestly, even in this demonstration, in this pseudo code,
中文字幕
there were a whole bunch of assumptions.
If you read these instructions one at a time
中文字幕
and you're holding the phone book yourself,
odds are you can execute this pseudocode, this algorithm.
中文字幕
But what does it really mean to, say, open to the middle of the phone book?
All of us have an intuitive understanding of what that means.
中文字幕
But honestly, if you were explaining that
to a kid or someone who's learning English or whatever language
中文字幕
for the first time, open to the middle of the phone book,
you should probably sets forth some assumptions.
中文字幕
OK, this thing in front of you has 1,000 pages, pieces of paper.
Turn to the 500th page, and let's call that the middle.
中文字幕
This would very quickly get tedious if all of us humans
are talking at that level of detail.
中文字幕
And so we abstract away with more sweeping
statements like open to the middle of the phone book,
中文字幕
but that's an abstraction.
And it's not quite as precise as is probably ideal,
中文字幕
especially feeding this algorithm to a newbie or to a robot or a computer.
But it's useful because we can then make a 12 step program instead of a 20 step
中文字幕
program by elaborating too much.
And for instance, throughout here too we had our loops and conditions
中文字幕
and so forth, but even call Mike.
What does that mean?
中文字幕
Well, if you imagine that the human knows how to use the phone,
then it goes without saying.
中文字幕
But if he or she also needs to be programmed to use the phone,
you've got to explain-- pick it up, hit this button, type
中文字幕
this sequence of buttons, and so forth.
So call Mike is also an abstraction.
中文字幕
So these abstractions are useful, but they can sometimes get in the way,
especially if you're not precise enough to program the computer correctly.
中文字幕
And to paint this picture, I thought we could begin a little heartedly here.
I brought some breakfast, if you didn't quite make it next door or beyond.
中文字幕
Just need a couple of volunteers if you're
comfortable appearing on stage and on the internet here.
中文字幕
Let me kind of-- there's a lot of lights here.
How about over there on the left and over here in the front?
中文字幕
Yeah, right there.
I think your hand was up.
中文字幕
Come on down.
And Brian, do you mind lending us a hand here, too?
中文字幕
Come on down.
If you want to take control here, let you go ahead
中文字幕
and switch over to another program for you.
What's your name?
中文字幕
JEAN: Jean.
Jean, David.
中文字幕
Nice to meet you.
Have a seat on the far left.
中文字幕
And your name?
ABBY: Hi, I'm Abby.
中文字幕
Nice to meet you as well.
On the far right if you could.
中文字幕
So Jean and Abby, do you want to say a little something about yourselves
quickly?
中文字幕
JEAN: I'm Jean.
I'm a Massachusetts native, and I'm taking CS for the first.
中文字幕
It's my first coding or anything.
Or I'm doing and I'm enjoying it.
中文字幕
Nice, glad to have you with us.
And Abby?
中文字幕
ABBY: Hi, I'm Abby.
I'm taking this as a sophomore, and I know nothing
中文字幕
about computers or computer science.
So I'm probably taking it stat on stat.
中文字幕
OK, well, nice to have you as well.
So in front of us is a whole bunch of ingredients,
中文字幕
and hopefully we can start this semester off gently.
And if we're successful, we'll actually have a quick bite here.
中文字幕
But we thought we'd defer to the audience here,
and Brian's going to scribe as we go.
中文字幕
And all we want to do this morning is just
make a peanut butter and jelly sandwich, one instruction at a time.
中文字幕
And each of us will just execute what we hear.
How does that sound?
中文字幕
All right, if someone could volunteer with the first instruction and Brian
will type it down.
中文字幕
Open bread.
Open bread we heard.
中文字幕
Open bread is the first instruction.
So each of you would like to execute open bread.
中文字幕
No, don't look at me.
All right, so we're kind of on our way.
中文字幕
I think Abby did it better certainly, but we did it correctly arguably.
So let's move on to step 2 and see if we can't improve.
中文字幕
Take out bread.
Welcome to the team now.
中文字幕
Nice, all right, step three.
Yeah.
中文字幕
Place two pieces of bread on the table.
Never mind the plates.
中文字幕
OK, step four.
Twist cover of jelly till it opens.
中文字幕
Thank you.
Step five?
中文字幕
Yeah?
Place the lid to the side.
中文字幕
Thank you.
Place the lid to the side.
中文字幕
I took some liberties myself.
Take the knife.
中文字幕
Peel off the cover of the jelly.
No covers on ours.
中文字幕
Stick knife into the bottle?
From the top.
中文字幕
Stick-- step nine.
Rotate hands so jelly ends up on.
中文字幕
Rotate hands so jelly ends up on--
OK, step-- quickly--
中文字幕
10.
Yes, step 10?
中文字幕
Pull out knife.
OK, step 11.
中文字幕
Jelly side down on bread.
All right, step 12.
中文字幕
Step 12, anyone?
Yes.
中文字幕
Thank you.
Step 13.
中文字幕
Pour jelly on bread.
JEAN: Pour jelly--
中文字幕
Pour jelly, jelly.
All of it?
中文字幕
OK, now you're just messing with us.
Step 14.
中文字幕
Put jelly down.
Thank you.
中文字幕
15?
Pick up peanut butter.
中文字幕
Take the lid off.
Take lid off.
中文字幕
Thank you.
Peel off lid.
中文字幕
Thank you.
Step 18?
中文字幕
Pick up knife by blunt end, scoop.
Scoop.
中文字幕
Step 20?
Put peanut butter on bread?
中文字幕
21?
Move the knife left to right.
中文字幕
Move-- move the knife left to right, please.
Left to right.
中文字幕
Step 22?
Put down knife.
中文字幕
Thank you.
23?
中文字幕
Put down jar.
24.
中文字幕
What was that?
Eat sandwich.
中文字幕
OK, I think we're--
well, why don't each take a bite?
中文字幕
And a round of applause, if we could, for our volunteers.
Thank you.
中文字幕
Mind if I take some for the row?
You can take some for the row if you'd like.
中文字幕
Thank you.
So-- thank you, Brian.
中文字幕
OK, now I need a minute.
Thank you.
中文字幕
So suffice it to say, this obviously demonstrated even more so
than the phone book example where our certain assumptions are
中文字幕
and our abstractions are.
And honestly, almost all the time those are useful.
中文字幕
And of course, we kind of hammed things up.
And I think the instructions were kind of helping with that here.
中文字幕
But when it comes time to program with Scratch and certainly with C
starting this week, you can't really make as many of those assumptions
中文字幕
anymore because, if you don't handle these corner cases
and if you don't think about what that instruction means,
中文字幕
you're going to get the proverbial spinning beachball or the hourglass
that you're familiar with on your Mac or PC.
中文字幕
The program is going to crash, something's
going to go wrong just because you miss some specificity or precision.
中文字幕
Now we're full of peanut butter.
So over time, we're going to find that, much like in Scratch,
中文字幕
we were able to make our own building blocks.
You might recall the short examples we did with the cough example
中文字幕
where I had cough 0 and then cough 1 and cough 2
where I was making my own puzzle piece within Scratch.
中文字幕
That was useful because, after that example theoretically,
I never again need to think about or worry about how to implement cough.
中文字幕
I can just use that abstraction.
But someone has to implement them, and sometimes it's
中文字幕
going to be other people who have come before us.
And sometimes it's going to be us.
中文字幕
So this isn't to say that programming ends up being so tedious
that you have to point out every little thing,
中文字幕
but you or someone does have to do that level of precision at least once.
And nicely enough in Scratch, MIT did most of that legwork for you.
中文字幕
We all had the building blocks with which
to make our own animation or game or artwork or the like.
中文字幕
But even then, you probably had to connect several dozen puzzle pieces
or even more to get those fundamentals to do
中文字幕
what it is that you wanted it to do.
So today we're going to start to transition from Scratch,
中文字幕
this graphical programming language, that while targeted at younger
students, is typically representative of a lot
中文字幕
of the same concepts that are now going to be laced throughout the semester.
But we're going to introduce today an older, more traditional language that's
中文字幕
just text based.
And as such it's a lot more powerful.
中文字幕
But at first glance, it's actually going to look a lot more cryptic.
In fact, instead of writing zeros and ones starting today,
中文字幕
we're instead going to write something like this.
Now if you've never programmed before, odds are, at first glance,
中文字幕
this does look pretty cryptic, and there's
a lot of symbols within it, punctuation from the keyboard.
中文字幕
There's probably some familiar English like words.
And frankly, even after doing Scratch anyone, even with no prior background,
中文字幕
can probably hazard a guess as to what this program written
in this other language called C does when you run it.
中文字幕
It just prints hello world.
Now granted there's a decent amount of overhead syntactically.
中文字幕
There's a bunch of stuff you have to type to make
this program do what you want it to do.
中文字幕
But at the end of the day, that's all it's going to do.
And this is among the simplest of programs
中文字幕
we're going to add to our puzzle pieces, so
to speak, today and see some of those same concepts
中文字幕
that we saw last time as well.
So let's do this first though.
中文字幕
Let me take a moment to compare Scratch to C
because the most important takeaway for today
中文字幕
is going to be that, even if the syntax doesn't look so obvious--
and frankly, even if your first minutes or hours
中文字幕
with writing your own code in C is frustrating because, oh,
dammit, you left off a semi-colon or, oh,
中文字幕
I had a parenthesis in the wrong place.
There's a lot of these stupid syntactic hangups
中文字幕
that make you feel quite often that you really aren't getting it.
But that's not the important stuff.
中文字幕
A lot of the syntax is the least important.
That's not at all fundamentally intellectually interesting.
中文字幕
So try to see past that, and try to take comfort in the fact
that it's the principles that are going to be important.
中文字幕
And honestly, just muscle memory and practice, all of the other stuff
that at first is going to be an occasional frustration,
中文字幕
it just starts to go away as you start to see
this for what it is and not for the syntax
中文字幕
alone that you see on first glance.
So this is to say this program on the right in C
中文字幕
is equivalent to what we did just a week ago with two puzzle pieces in Scratch.
Now there isn't going to be a green flag on my Mac or my PC
中文字幕
as we move forward that you can just click.
We're going to run these programs in a little different way,
中文字幕
but that's all the code on the right is doing.
It's equivalent to the code on the left.
中文字幕
So let's do this again and again for just a few of those concepts
from last time, and then we'll start writing some of our own programs.
中文字幕
So this was an example, this purple block, of what concept in programming?
Yeah, a function.
中文字幕
So it was a verb.
It was an action, and we're going to call those generally functions.
中文字幕
They just have functionality built into them.
So how do we do this in C?
中文字幕
Well, you might remember from just a moment ago,
because one of the lines of code was representative of this,
中文字幕
it had some of this syntax.
So in fact, if I were to translate the block
中文字幕
on the left in Scratch to the equivalent code in this other text based
language called C, I'm going to start by writing print
中文字幕
and then open parenthesis and then close parenthesis.
And those parentheses represent the oval, the white oval on the left,
中文字幕
that we typed hello world into before.
Now in C, it's not quite as literal as that.
中文字幕
The function, or the verb, is actually not called print.
It's called printf, and the F stands for formatted.
中文字幕
And it just means that in C you can actually
format your text in different ways.
中文字幕
So we'll see that before long, and it turns out
that you don't just write hello world between those parentheses
中文字幕
like we did in Scratch.
You also actually have to surround them with double quotes in C.
中文字幕
Not such a big deal, but something you didn't have to do before.
But in C, you're also going to generally want
中文字幕
to be super specific to the computer.
And when you want the cursor the text on the screen
中文字幕
to move down to the next line, you need to tell the computer that
by literally typing backslash n.
中文字幕
The human is not going to see a backslash and an n.
He or she is actually going to see the cursor move
中文字幕
to the next line of the screen like in Google Docs
or in Microsoft Word or the like.
中文字幕
But this just speaks to the precision that you
need to have when talking to a computer at this level
中文字幕
and not just with the puzzle pieces.
And then one last thing-- and I alluded to it earlier
中文字幕
because it's the bane of a lot of programmers early on.
Most lines of code in C have to end in a semi-colon.
中文字幕
That's the sort of code equivalent of a period in an English
or some other languages sentence.
中文字幕
So that's it.
It took us a little while to build that up.
中文字幕
But that's all it is.
The idea on the left of saying something is the same in C
中文字幕
as printing something with this function called printf.
And before I forge ahead with some other comparisons,
中文字幕
any questions on just this translation?
How do you write backslash n?
中文字幕
Good, so thinking ahead, this would seem to make it hard to literally show
the user backslash n.
中文字幕
Well, it turns out that this backslash, because it's not
a terribly common character, the programming world
中文字幕
uses it as what's called an escape character.
It's one that you use when you want to escape information and show it
中文字幕
in a slightly different way.
So the way you would show literally to the human
中文字幕
a actual backslash n is to actually in your code
do backslash backslash n because the second backslash is
中文字幕
like saying treat the next character special
and actually show it to the human.
中文字幕
And there's other such examples of that.
So how about this one?
中文字幕
This orange block was an example of one concept in Scratch?
Yeah, so this was a variable, like an x and y in algebra.
中文字幕
This was just a placeholder for data, and you could store numbers.
It turns out you can store words.
中文字幕
You can store other things too in other languages.
So in C, we're going to do this.
中文字幕
We're going to say, literally, the name of the variable we want-- for instance,
counter.
中文字幕
But we could call anything we want--
equals zero if we're setting it initially equal to zero.
中文字幕
But C is a little more pedantic.
You've also got to tell the computer, the type of variable I want
中文字幕
is specifically for an integer, otherwise abbreviated int.
So you have to tell the computer in advance what type of data
中文字幕
you're going to store on it.
And take a guess.
中文字幕
You've got to finish the thought ion C. What more do we need to add to the--
yeah, just a semi-colon.
中文字幕
And that's it.
It looks a little more cryptic, but the idea is fundamentally the same.
中文字幕
So what if we wanted to do this in Scratch?
Change counter by 1-- this was equivalent to incrementing or adding 1
中文字幕
to counter.
Well, let me go ahead and propose that you could literally just
中文字幕
do this in C. Set counter equal to whatever counter currently is plus 1.
That seems to be the right intuition.
中文字幕
And now notice, what's key to note here is
that this equal sign isn't saying that counter equals counter plus 1
中文字幕
because that just doesn't seem possible.
If you pick any value for counter, like the number 1,
中文字幕
well, one definitely does not equal 1 plus 1, which is 2.
And 1 does not equal 2, and you can come up
中文字幕
with an infinite number of worrisome incorrect comparisons.
So the equal sign in C, like a lot of languages we'll see in the class,
中文字幕
actually means assignment.
Copy the value on the right into the value on the left.
中文字幕
So set counter equal to whatever it is plus 1.
What?
中文字幕
We've got to finish the thought.
So we need a semi-colon.
中文字幕
I don't though need to remention int, and why might that be?
Yeah, I already told the computer it's an integer.
中文字幕
You don't need to repeat yourself by mentioning int again,
assuming in this context, even though we're looking at it just on the slide,
中文字幕
has actually been created before just like you did
with Scratch by saying make a variable.
中文字幕
So it turns out you can be a little more succinct in C and a lot of languages.
If you find this a little tedious to type-- and it's a little verbose.
中文字幕
It's a bunch of keystrokes.
You can actually abbreviate it with just this.
中文字幕
So plus equals is just syntactic sugar, as a programmer would say.
It's just a nice fancy feature that lets you write fewer words or characters
中文字幕
but do the same thing.
And frankly, we can do a little better.
中文字幕
And if you've taken a PCS, you might have seen this in Java as well.
You can also simplify this even more to just counter plus plus semi-colon.
中文字幕
So that's it-- all equivalent.
This is just a little more efficient.
中文字幕
And as you get more comfortable programming,
saving keystrokes just saves you time.
中文字幕
Now this of course was an example of what in Scratch by contrast?
Yeah, we called this a condition.
中文字幕
And it had a Boolean expression that we were asking a question of.
In this case, we're apparently asking in Scratch is x less than y and, if so,
中文字幕
say it on the screen.
So how might we translate this to see?
中文字幕
Well, it turns out we can quite simply translate this one pretty literally.
We've seen almost all of the building blocks thus far,
中文字幕
but we do have to introduce a little something new here.
Notice that the printf line is almost identical to what
中文字幕
I used earlier for just hello world.
I've obviously just changed the words in it, but I still have the backslash n.
中文字幕
I still have the quotes, still have the semi-colon.
So the rest of that is the same.
中文字幕
Now if is new, but this is a one to one translation.
Scratch calls it if.
中文字幕
C calls it if.
And the only additional thing you need in C
中文字幕
is parentheses around the Boolean expression.
So that's what takes the place of the little green block there.
中文字幕
And then assuming x and y are indeed variables
that we created earlier, you can just compare them like this
中文字幕
and you can use greater than and other symbols for comparison as well.
But there is something a little interesting, and most of us
中文字幕
don't often have occasion to even use these keys on our keyboard.
Curly braces, on a US keyboard they tend to be
中文字幕
over on the top right above your Enter key.
These are just C's equivalent of this shape.
中文字幕
Notice that most of the yellow blocks in Scratch
had this embracing or this embracing shape to them.
中文字幕
You can simulate that in C by having what's called an open curly brace
and then a closed curly brace.
中文字幕
So that's the same exact idea.
Now as an aside, you don't technically always need these curly braces.
中文字幕
If you just got a one liner like this, you
can omit them as you might see online or in textbooks.
中文字幕
But we'll just always draw them for consistency so that the C code always
looks like this.
中文字幕
What if you wanted to express this, though?
If x is less than y, then say x is less than y, else say x is not less than y.
中文字幕
Well, it turns out this is almost identical.
The first four lines, perfectly the same as before.
中文字幕
But it turns out in C, you can literally say else
after that closing curly brace.
中文字幕
And then just print out alternatively whatever it is you want to say.
So this is like the fork in the road.
中文字幕
If you go one way, say this.
If you go the other way, say this other thing.
中文字幕
Any questions on these comparisons thus far?
Yeah.
中文字幕
Should we put the first bracket on the same line as the if?
Really good question.
中文字幕
Can you or do you put the curly brace on the same line is the if?
You can, and we're going to talk about this the next couple of weeks,
中文字幕
this matter of style.
There are different ways I could express this exact same code.
中文字幕
Frankly, I could write out all of this code with no spaces whatsoever.
In fact, just to make that point, if I go ahead and just open up a simple text
中文字幕
editor here--
not to actually program, but to just type something--
中文字幕
I could actually do something like this if x less than y.
Then go ahead and print out x is less than y backslash n semi-colon curly
中文字幕
brace else print and so forth--
completely unreadable at the end of the day or unmaintainable,
中文字幕
especially when the code gets complicated.
But whitespace does not tend to matter to the computer,
中文字幕
but it does matter to the human.
And as you're alluding to in some languages,
中文字幕
it's actually conventional to do this, where you actually
keep the curly brace on the same line.
中文字幕
And indeed, you might see textbooks do this as well.
Some people will even do this.
中文字幕
These are all long story short matters of style.
In CS50, in the earliest weeks of the class,
中文字幕
we're going to insist that everyone follow the same style so
that we have some basis for comparison.
中文字幕
But eventually, this is the kind of thing
that, like in your own English writing or whatever language you
中文字幕
tend to write in, you have your own stylistic or linguistic flair to it.
Code has that as well.
中文字幕
Other questions?
Yeah.
中文字幕
When you establish the counter-variable,
do you always have to say what it is equal to,
中文字幕
or can you just say int counter section?
Really good question.
中文字幕
When you declare a variable, create a variable,
do you have to set it equal to something right away?
中文字幕
Short answer, no.
And we'll see examples of that before long, where you can actually
中文字幕
say give me a variable called counter, but don't actually
set it equal to some value.
中文字幕
Come back to that in a bit.
So what if we want to add this logic?
中文字幕
Frankly, in Scratch it's starting to look a little overwhelming.
But this is just a three way fork in the road.
中文字幕
If x is less than y, say so, else if x is greater than y,
say so, else if x equals y, then go ahead and say they're equal.
中文字幕
And in C, we can do this translation pretty directly as well.
In fact, now the first eight lines of code
中文字幕
are identical to before except this middle one
here where I'm adding a second Boolean expression.
中文字幕
Is x greater than y?
And then I have this third condition, else if x equals y.
中文字幕
But there seems to be a typo perhaps or something anomalous here.
So anything jump out?
中文字幕
Yeah.
I have a double equal sign, which maybe is just a typographical error
中文字幕
on my part, but turns out it's not.
This is deliberate.
中文字幕
But why?
This seems like our first example of where Scratch doesn't really
中文字幕
map perfectly to C?
Well, because the equal sign is like an assignment.
中文字幕
And so counting the equal sign actively sets it equal--
Exactly.
中文字幕
We already a moment ago decided as humans-- or really, years ago-- equals
is actually in the context of C going to be assignment-- copy
中文字幕
the value from the right to the value on the left.
And so we kind of painted ourselves into a corner.
中文字幕
We still as humans, as programmers, want to be
able to express the notion of equality and comparing.
中文字幕
But if we've already used the equal sign for assignment,
we need another pattern of symbols to represent equality.
中文字幕
And as it turns out, humans just chose two equal signs instead--
so slightly different from Scratch.
中文字幕
The reason Scratch does it this way is because you don't really
want to have to get into those weeds certainly
中文字幕
when the target audience is 8-year-olds just
learning to program in the first place.
中文字幕
It's not important nor is it really important for us.
But for us there's going to be a logical difference
中文字幕
because, if we use the wrong one, the behavior is going to be wrong.
If we had just one equal sign, we would literally be changing x to equal y
中文字幕
rather than just comparing it.
Was there a hand in here?
中文字幕
Yeah.
Just a quick question.
中文字幕
So if you wanted to express greater than or equal to,
would you write equal and greater than?
中文字幕
Good question.
If you wanted to express greater than or equal to, how might you do that?
中文字幕
It turns out there are ways to do that.
And if I go ahead and just give myself someplace to draw here for a moment,
中文字幕
you can actually indeed do less than or equal or greater than or equal.
There's no way on a typical keyboard to put them atop each other
中文字幕
like you might recall for math.
You just put them next to each other.
中文字幕
Well, it depends.
I want the double equal sign here because I
中文字幕
want to explicitly check this third case and say x is equal to y.
So that was my goal.
中文字幕
But logically, this is not necessary.
Let's make the program a little better designed.
中文字幕
How many possible cases are there when comparing two integers, x
and y, for greater than, less than, or equality?
中文字幕
Well, I kinda of just answered the question, didn't I?
Three.
中文字幕
Excellent!
There's three scenarios there-- x is either less than or greater than
中文字幕
or equal to.
And I'm hard pressed to think of a fourth.
中文字幕
So do I need this amount of specificity?
What could I do to give myself a slight optimization,
中文字幕
improve the code just a little bit just to save myself
a little bit of time writing it and maybe even the computer
中文字幕
a little time running it?
Yeah.
中文字幕
You don't need the last condition.
Yeah, I don't need the last condition because,
中文字幕
if we all agree logically that either x is less than y or greater than y
or maybe equal to y, well, if there's only a third and final case that
中文字幕
can just be my so-called else.
Just make that be the so-called default case.
中文字幕
And in fact, even though this is what most people would
call an over optimization, you are saving the computer some time.
中文字幕
Because suppose that x does in fact equal y
and they're both the value number 1.
中文字幕
So is 1 less than 1 when this line of code is executed?
Yes or no?
中文字幕
No, obviously not.
1 is not less than 1.
中文字幕
So this code does not execute.
But the Boolean expression is evaluated, so to speak.
中文字幕
The question is asked.
Is 1 greater than 1?
中文字幕
No, and so this code is not executed, but this Boolean expression is.
So we just spent another step or second or however fast the computer is.
中文字幕
Is 1 equal to 1?
Yeah, it is.
中文字幕
So this actually prints.
But to your point, you don't need to ask that question.
中文字幕
And in fact, you just increased by a factor of 50%
how many questions you're asking.
中文字幕
So you just wasted a little bit of time.
Now as an aside, our Macs and PCs and phones
中文字幕
these days, I mean, again, they're operating at like a gigahertz
speed, one billion things per second.
中文字幕
So in practice, who cares if you're asking that third question?
And frankly, if it makes your code more readable or to your teaching fellow
中文字幕
or to a colleague or friend who's working on the program for you,
then that's great.
中文字幕
If it's more clear from the code what's going on, leave it that way.
But these are the kinds of design decisions that we'll now make.
中文字幕
And arguably this version of the scratch program and this version of the C code
is just a little better designed because why
中文字幕
write more code than you need to express the exact same idea.
So what about this?
中文字幕
This was a loop in Scratch.
This was an infinite loop because it was just forever saying hello world.
中文字幕
Now in C, this gets a little less directly translated.
It turns out c uses the key word while.
中文字幕
So there is no forever keyword in C, but there is the word while.
And of course, I'm going to use my curly braces--
中文字幕
curly braces, curly brackets to encompass the following lines of code.
The line of code I want in there is just another printf.
中文字幕
So that's the exact same as before, but it's not sufficient to just say while.
It turns out that while wants you to ask it a question every time
中文字幕
the loop executes.
And it's going to check that question.
中文字幕
And if the answer is yes, it's going to run the loop.
But if the answer being asked in C is ever no or false,
中文字幕
it's going to not execute the code and it's just
going to move on to any further lines of code lower down in the file.
中文字幕
So in C, you actually need a pair parentheses after the keyword while.
And then you need to ask a question.
中文字幕
You need to ask a question like, is x less than y
or a question like is x greater than y or is x equal to y.
中文字幕
But none of those scenarios apply because the whole purpose
of this Scratch block is literally to do something forever.
中文字幕
So what's a question we could ask to which the answer is surely true?
Does 1 equal 1?
中文字幕
We could contrive an arbitrary but very met mathematically correct scenario.
We can just say just 1 equal equal 1.
中文字幕
But it turns out you can be even more succinct because in C there's
a couple of keywords, one of which is true, one of which is false.
中文字幕
And the word true is by definition always true,
and the word false is by definition always false.
中文字幕
So you don't need to contrive some arbitrary but correct idea
of does 1 equal equal 1 or does 50 equal equal 50.
中文字幕
You don't need to just come up with some arbitrary solution.
You can literally just say true because that key word true never changes value.
中文字幕
So even though this is a little weird looking,
it's how you induce something to happen forever.
中文字幕
You asked the same question again and assume that the question always
has the same answer of true.
中文字幕
Any questions on that one?
Yeah, in the back.
中文字幕
Do spaces matter?
Can you take out the space between y and 0?
中文字幕
Good question.
Do spaces matter?
中文字幕
Short answer, no, not in this case.
You can in fact delete all of the space here
中文字幕
except for the one in the English phrase,
and it would still be functionally correct.
中文字幕
You can even add spaces anywhere you want.
You can make this taller by hitting Enter a bunch of times,
中文字幕
tabs, spaces around the word true.
All of the examples I"ll show here today and you'll see in the coming weeks are
中文字幕
the better way to do things because they're more readable.
But again, as you get more comfortable with code
中文字幕
or if you're coming in with some prior experience,
you might already have your own opinions.
中文字幕
And frankly, this is just a religious debate
among programmers, which is the right way to write your code.
中文字幕
And that's fine.
Once you get comfy, so long as you're consistent is the most important thing.
中文字幕
You don't need to adhere to one person's or the other.
So how does this code work logically?
中文字幕
Well, the first thing the computer, your Mac or PC or your phone
or whatever is going to do, it's going to ask the question.
中文字幕
Well, true.
Well, true is always true.
中文字幕
So it's going to proceed to execute the line of code.
But after it does, because that's the entirety of the code that's
中文字幕
in between the curly braces, we could have more lines.
These are just short programs.
中文字幕
The computer is going to check, OK, is true still true.
Yes.
中文字幕
So it's going to execute it again.
Then it's going to ask the question again.
中文字幕
Is true still true?
Yes, so it's going to execute the code again,
中文字幕
and this is going to repeat literally forever.
But what if you don't want to repeat something forever?
中文字幕
What if you only want to repeat it 50 times?
Scratch doesn't make you think very hard about this.
中文字幕
People just figure out how to keep track of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and all the way
up to 50 and then stop.
中文字幕
That's nice.
It makes it easy to use the block.
中文字幕
C and a lot of languages aren't quite that user friendly.
You will see later in the semester that newer languages are
中文字幕
a little closer to what Scratch offers.
But in C, we need to be more explicit, but this
中文字幕
is a chance to use some of these more primitive building blocks.
In C, the equivalent of repeat is going to be the proposition for just because,
中文字幕
for now.
And then, just as before, if we want to do something
中文字幕
again and again within this loop, we're going
to use the curly braces, similar to the little orange block there.
中文字幕
And then what am I going to do?
I'm going to do this every time, 50 times hopefully, print out hello world.
中文字幕
So now I just need to figure out and see how to express
the number of times specifically 50.
中文字幕
So it turns out in C-- use parentheses again--
this is going to be a pretty common characteristic of a lot of the code
中文字幕
we write.
And then you need to do three things.
中文字幕
The burden is now going to be on us the programmer
to keep track of how many times we want to execute this code to how many times
中文字幕
we've already executed this code and then constantly make sure
that one does not exceed the other.
中文字幕
So we stop once we hit 50.
So what's the fundamental construct that we use to keep track of anything
中文字幕
in a program?
A counter, which was an example of a variable.
中文字幕
So we just need to use a variable.
Now it's actually going to be inside of the parentheses this time.
中文字幕
So it's not on its own as it was just a bit ago, but the syntax is the same.
I could call it counter, but the reality is that the convention in programming
中文字幕
is just to use shorter variables when you're just doing something mundane.
And if all you're doing is looping--
中文字幕
i stands for integer, is sort of many programmers' go-to variable name
rather than the more verbose but correct counter or whatever.
中文字幕
So this says, hey, computer, give me a variable called i.
Let me store integers or ints in it and set the initial value to 0.
中文字幕
Why?
Well, almost everyone in this room probably starts counting from 1.
中文字幕
Computers just tend to start counting from 0.
But why?
中文字幕
What's the rationale for starting to count from 0
perhaps based on last week?
中文字幕
Why does that kind of makes sense?
Yeah, what do you think?
中文字幕
Well, because it's ones and zeros, and it's binary.
Yeah, it's just ones and zeros, and what's
中文字幕
the smallest number, negative values aside,
that you can represent in binary?
中文字幕
Well, it's just 0, 0, 0, a bunch of zeros.
So why would you waste that representation,
中文字幕
that permutation of bits?
Let's just start counting at 0 and then add to that.
中文字幕
So you can start counting from 1 in C, but the convention in most languages
is count from 0.
中文字幕
So we'll get off on that foot as well.
And you might recall even that in our PBJ, for the peanut butter and jelly--
中文字幕
not for the PDJ code--
for the phone pseudo code, I actually deliberately started
中文字幕
numbering the lines from 0 to 1 to 2 for that same intuition.
So here's how you then say to the computer check, if you would,
中文字幕
whether i is less than 50.
Now, initially it's obviously going to be less than 50
中文字幕
because zero is less than 50 but that same condition is
going to be checked again and again and again as this loop executes.
中文字幕
And then recall from before, we can just plus plus a variable to add 1 to it.
We can do this more verbosely.
中文字幕
We could say i equals i plus 1, but it's just
more conventional to write i plus plus just
中文字幕
to say the same thing more tersely.
So what happens next logically?
中文字幕
That's the code I've written.
What does the computer do with it?
中文字幕
Well, it initialises i to 0 and prepare to store integers in it.
It checks the condition just in case you initialized it too big of a value.
中文字幕
You might not want the loop to execute at all.
But obviously 0 is less than 50.
中文字幕
So this line of code executes.
Take a guess as to what happens next.
中文字幕
Yeah, you probably want to do i plus plus
because you're done executing all the lines of code
中文字幕
in between the curly braces, even though there's just one.
So let's go ahead and increment i.
中文字幕
So i is now 1.
Let's now make sure-- is 1 less than 50?
中文字幕
Obviously.
Execute the code.
中文字幕
I plus plus-- is 2 less than 50.
Obviously execute the code. i plus plus-- is 3 less than 50, obviously.
中文字幕
Now go ahead and execute the code, and again and again and again.
And at some point, we're going to get up to i equals 49, and is 49 less than 50?
中文字幕
Obviously.
So we print out hello world.
中文字幕
And then i plus plus kicks in, and then it's, is 50 less than 50.
No.
中文字幕
So wait that feels like a logical error, no?
Should I be checking if i is less than or equal to 50?
中文字幕
Yeah, because if I started from 0, I already
spent that one additional cycle.
中文字幕
So I can count from 0 through 49 which seems to work or from 1 through 50,
but the convention in programming honestly
中文字幕
is typically to start counting at some value
and then count up to but not through some value just because.
中文字幕
But logically, you can implement this in half a dozen different ways most
likely.
中文字幕
Let's look at one final example that allowed us
to actually get user input in Scratch.
中文字幕
Recall that we used this block to actually get
the name of someone in lecture, and we also
中文字幕
in the animation with the gingerbread house used it to get yes or no--
do you want the cupcake or the apple or the like.
中文字幕
So this is an example of a function in Scratch
that actually takes input like the sentence what's your name,
中文字幕
but it also returns a value, which in this case
was just hard coded in Scratch by MIT to be called answer.
中文字幕
So it's like a special variable called answer,
but effectively it's being handed back to the user.
中文字幕
So how might we think about this?
In C it turns out that you can express this line of code a little more
中文字幕
verbosely than before but using a new function called get string--
so get underscore string is the name of the function.
中文字幕
The underscore is convention in C. If you ever want to have a space,
you can't have spaces in the names of functions.
中文字幕
So people just started using underscores like you might in your own social media
user names and the like-- is a convention there as well.
中文字幕
Here's the sentence I want to display, and I'm
going to start calling this more formally a string.
中文字幕
A string in a programming language is just a sequence of characters.
It's a word, it's a phrase, it's a character, it's a paragraph.
中文字幕
This is a string.
Anything between double quotes is a string in C,
中文字幕
and the backslash n it's just end of line as before.
We still already have the semi-colon, but this
中文字幕
isn't quite a literal translation of what's going on just yet
because I also now need to do something with the answer.
中文字幕
So if get string is a function that actually gets input from the user,
as via his or her keyboard, just like the blue block in Scratch, in C
中文字幕
we need to be a little more explicit as to where
we're putting the return value from that function, what it is it's handing back.
中文字幕
And so I can store in a variable called answer.
I could call it anything I want.
中文字幕
But for consistency with Scratch, let's call it answer.
But recall what we have to do in C anytime we create a variable.
中文字幕
We have to be more precise.
Yeah.
中文字幕
Define its class as a string.
We have to define its-- let me call it a type or class,
中文字幕
if you've taken a previous class.
It's type and it's not going to be an int because probably the words being
中文字幕
typed in are not numbers.
It's going to be this time what I just called it a string.
中文字幕
And so, indeed, we would declare the variable on the left
by saying give me a string, call it answer,
中文字幕
and assign to it whatever's on the right.
Well, what's on the right?
中文字幕
What is on the right is whatever this function
get string comes back with and gets stored from right to left.
中文字幕
So how do I now say this person's name?
Well, in Scratch I just say and then I drag and drop the answer variable,
中文字幕
and it's done.
What's the function in C with which we can say something, though,
中文字幕
on the screen?
So printf, print a formatted string, even though we haven't really seen
中文字幕
any formatting yet until now.
It turns out in C, You have to actually tell
中文字幕
d if you're not passing in a hard coded string or sentence,
you have to pass to printf what's called a format code or a format string--
中文字幕
this first input to printf.
Now printf apparently seems to take two things.
中文字幕
The first is this one before the comma.
The second is the thing after the comma.
中文字幕
And we've not seen this before yet in C. So printf
is being told, go ahead and print out a string that looks like this.
中文字幕
Percent S is a placeholder, and S stands for string.
And that literally is a placeholder saying,
中文字幕
printf, I'm going to give you a string to plug in to this first input.
What is that string?
中文字幕
Literally, the answer variable.
Now it feels like we're jumping through hoops here.
中文字幕
It would have been nice to just say printf, open parenthesis, answer,
close parenthesis, semi-colon, and be done with it.
中文字幕
That's just not the way printf works.
In older versions, you could maybe do something
中文字幕
a little more simple like that.
But honestly, we're not typically going to be printing out
中文字幕
just what the human typed in.
After all, this is kind of a stupid example at the moment.
中文字幕
I'm typing in a word.
You're just saying it on the screen.
中文字幕
We already decided in Scratch that's kind of lame.
It'd would be nice to at least have the program, not just
中文字幕
say David or whatever the name is-- but what did we do last time?
Like hello comma David.
中文字幕
But this would seem to give us that capability.
Right now I'm literally just printing out the human's name in C,
中文字幕
but let me change this ever so slightly just as we did in Scratch.
Recall that in C we did this green block of join where I literally
中文字幕
get past join two arguments.
The first one was hello comma space.
中文字幕
The second one was answer, and this concatenated.
This combined back to back those two strings.
中文字幕
Well, in C, thanks to printf, we can do that same thing.
It's just a different syntax.
中文字幕
Printf still gets one argument first, that is, the string you want to format,
ergo the F in printf.
中文字幕
But this time I'm going to literally say H-E-L-L-O comma space percent S
for string and then give printf a second argument,
中文字幕
which is its instruction to go ahead and plug in whatever this variable is
to whatever this placeholder is.
中文字幕
And so here we've now joined the two strings effectively and thus
was born our first formatted string.
中文字幕
Well, any questions then on that?
Yeah.
中文字幕
What if you wanted to say something extra after it?
What if you want to say something extra after?
中文字幕
You could certainly continue the logic.
You don't have to end this quoted expression
中文字幕
with percent S. You could say, hello, comma percent S
comma, nice to meet you.
中文字幕
And then what printf will do is it's only
going to substitute that variable called answer where the percent S is.
中文字幕
And if you want to give 2% S's, you could just add another comma here
and pass in another variable and a third variable and even more,
中文字幕
thus formatting the string even more detailed.
Question over here.
中文字幕
Yeah.
Other questions?
中文字幕
Yeah, in the back.
How do you make a distinction between the placeholders
中文字幕
if you have different variables?
How do you make a distinction between the placeholders
中文字幕
if you have different variables?
It's the ordering from left to right.
中文字幕
So in this case, it's a trivial example because there's
only one variable and one placeholder.
中文字幕
But if as you were hinting, I had multiple percent S something something
something, percent S something something something,
中文字幕
I would just make sure that I pass printf the first variable comma
the second variable comma the third variable and so forth left to right.
中文字幕
Other questions?
Yeah.
中文字幕
Why is there no backslash n?
Oh, damn it.
中文字幕
Because I screwed up and didn't include that and I
was going to fix it after class quickly.
中文字幕
Bug, it's a bug.
Yeah.
中文字幕
What if you wanted to use the int twice in the string?
So you wanted to say, hello, David, hi, David.
中文字幕
Sure, same exact thing--
comma answer, comma answer with 2% S. If you want to say the same variable twice
中文字幕
in two places for whatever reason, two placeholders and then answer comma
answer to plug that in twice.
中文字幕
Other que-- yeah.
Is percent a universal placeholder in terms of integers?
中文字幕
No, and we're going to see some others in just a bit.
It turns out there's others.
中文字幕
It's percent i integer, and there's going
to be even more than that-- percent c for a single character and more.
中文字幕
Other questions?
Yeah.
中文字幕
Since the backslash n is a variable, would you put it after n?
So will you put it in the quotation?
中文字幕
Good question.
If I did have correctly-- and if this weren't a PDF,
中文字幕
I would just edit it on the fly--
if I had the percent n, it always has to go in the formatted string,
中文字幕
in the first argument.
So the only thing that comes after printf's first argument
中文字幕
is optionally variable comma variable comma variable comma variable.
Other questions?
中文字幕
so Let's go ahead and actually do something with code.
I'm going to go ahead and open up another window,
中文字幕
and this is a tool called with CS50 Sandbox,
and this is a tool via the web by a which you can actually play with code.
中文字幕
And I'll show in just a moment how I get to this particular location,
but let me first explain the user interface much like we started off
中文字幕
our conversation with Scratch.
So I need a place to write code.
中文字幕
The reality is I could just use my own Mac.
I could just use my own PC.
中文字幕
Frankly, I could even use certain mobile devices these days.
But then we would have hundreds of other people in the class
中文字幕
all with slightly different configurations
on their Max and their PCs and their phones and the like.
中文字幕
And so everyone would have different software and different settings,
and they just never works very well.
中文字幕
So at the beginning of the course, we just
standardize everything by actually using a web based environment
中文字幕
just like Scratch is, whereby we'll all have access to the exact same computer
but virtualized in the so-called cloud.
中文字幕
If you've ever wondered what the cloud is,
it just means other people's server somewhere on the internet
中文字幕
that people can use for free or to rent and not
have to host those physical servers themselves.
中文字幕
So CS50 Sandbox, just like Scratch, is a cloud based application
that someone else wrote that's hosted on the internet,
中文字幕
and the user interface, at first glance, looks just like this.
There are only two components to it.
中文字幕
At the top of the user interface of CS50 Sandbox
is just a code editor, a very simple text editor
中文字幕
similar in spirit to Google Docs and Microsoft Word and so forth
but much simpler.
中文字幕
There's no formatting.
There's no bold facing and centering.
中文字幕
You can just type words of text.
Down here is the so-called terminal window,
中文字幕
but we'll come back to that in just a moment.
Let me go ahead and write my first program.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and write include standard IO dot age
int main void open curly brace printf hello world backslash and semi-colon,
中文字幕
done.
Now few people in this room could probably whip up a apparent program
中文字幕
that quickly unless you do have prior background.
And if you did take APCS or something else, it looks kind of like Java
中文字幕
but not quite the same.
But this is my first program.
中文字幕
Now recall from earlier this was the black and white program
we saw on the slide just a little bit ago.
中文字幕
And even if you didn't quite appreciate what all the funky syntax is doing,
all of us probably had the intuition of what this program does,
中文字幕
which is just to print out the words at the end of the day hello world.
And we'll tease apart in just a bit what all these various lines are doing.
中文字幕
But the interesting part is what's highlighted in green here,
and this is just one of the features of CS50 Sandbox.
中文字幕
It will color code different concepts within your code
so that they just jump out at you.
中文字幕
The colors aren't actually there.
You don't have to color code things yourself.
中文字幕
It just does it automatically so you can see the different components
just like MIT colorizes is the various Scratch puzzle pieces the same.
中文字幕
So this is a program that I want to call hello.
It's in a file.
中文字幕
This is just a tab up top called hello dot C
because it turns out, when you write a program in C,
中文字幕
you save it in files by human convention whatever dot C as the file extension,
so to speak.
中文字幕
How do I run this program?
There's no green flag to click, which Scratch gave us.
中文字幕
So how do I actually run the program.
And frankly, moreover, the green flag seems to be the least of my concerns.
中文字幕
What is the language that any computer understands
whether it's my Mac here or the cloud server where this thing is?
中文字幕
Zeros and ones, right?
And we started with that overwhelming slide of a lots of 0's and 1's, and
中文字幕
that is the point we need to get to.
But hopefully, we ourselves don't have to write at that level of tedium.
中文字幕
So we need some way of converting this code
from C, which we'll start calling source code, which is the English like code we
中文字幕
see on the screen that's mildly pleasurable to write as opposed
to just zeros and ones.
中文字幕
But we nonetheless need to convert it somehow to zeros and ones.
And so the way we can do this is essentially as follows.
中文字幕
If we have what we'll start calling our source code, which can be written,
in our case, in C, but you can write source code in Java, in C++, in Python,
中文字幕
in dozens of other language.
Source code's a generic term.
中文字幕
That just means the code that we humans have written.
We need some way of converting it into zeros and ones, which
中文字幕
henceforth we're just going to call machine code, which
feels like a reasonable name.
中文字幕
It's the zeros and ones that a machine understands.
How does a machine know what zeros and ones to understand?
中文字幕
Well, that's the whole reasoning behind having CPU, Central Processing
Unit, the brains of a computer.
中文字幕
They are just hardwired at the factory, so
to speak, at Intel's factory to understand
中文字幕
certain patterns of zeros and ones.
But the point for us now is we need to take a source code, like the C program
中文字幕
I wrote a moment ago that's supposed to print hello world,
and somehow convert it to machine code.
中文字幕
So it turns out this is the step that humans who've come before us
have solved for us.
中文字幕
Other humans have already written programs
that we're going to start calling a compiler that allows us
中文字幕
to convert source code to machine code.
It's just one additional step.
中文字幕
This step did not exist in Scratch, but we're
going to run a program that's generally called a compiler that we pass
中文字幕
our program to as input, and we get as output machine code, thereby
perfectly bringing us full circle to what computer science is
中文字幕
is in now the context of programming-- input
source code, outputs machine code.
中文字幕
The algorithm or the special software we're going to use in just a moment is
called a compiler that just converts one to the other so that none of us have
中文字幕
to ever think about or write in 0's and 1's.
So it's a little old school how you do this.
中文字幕
In Scratch, you obviously just hit the green flag and MIT
and all those folks took care of it for you.
中文字幕
We have to be a little more manual about this,
and that's where the second piece of CS50 Sandbox user interface
中文字幕
comes into play.
Notice I have a blinking prompt here.
中文字幕
There's dollar sign at left, which is just a common convention.
A dollar sign tends to in these types of computers represent a prompt.
中文字幕
It's waiting for me to type something, and indeed it's literally blinking,
waiting for me to type something.
中文字幕
This is an example of a terminal window, and your own iMac and your own PC
actually has or can't have this exact same feature.
中文字幕
It's just all of us operate with graphical user interfaces these days.
So we've got buttons and menus and things
中文字幕
to drag and click, but back in the day--
and typically in programming-- you don't bother with these aesthetics.
中文字幕
You actually get your hands dirtier with just the keyboard alone typing
anything you want to do.
中文字幕
And at first, it might feel like a regression.
Like, why are we giving up all these beautiful amenities
中文字幕
of modern computers?
But it's more powerful, and it's more explicit.
中文字幕
It lets you do exactly what you want to do by sending commands to the computer.
So this is my terminal 1.
中文字幕
I can create others just to have multiple windows,
but this is giving me access to the underlying server that I now
中文字幕
have access to.
So if any of you, when it comes time to the first problem set,
中文字幕
log into the same tool, you don't all have the same environment.
You all have your own isolated copies of the same software but your own storage
中文字幕
space, so to speak.
So I need to somehow convert hello dot C to zeros and ones.
中文字幕
And the way I'm going to do this is like this--
clang, which stands for C language, hello dot C enter.
中文字幕
And the fact that I see nothing happening is actually an amazing thing
because there's an infinite number of things, frankly, that can go wrong,
中文字幕
and the computer will happily yell at you
with cryptic looking error messages if any of those things do go wrong.
中文字幕
So seeing nothing but another blinking prompt with the dollar
sign is actually a good thing.
中文字幕
My code has somehow been converted to zeros and ones.
Where are those zeros and ones?
中文字幕
Well, by convention, they are stored in a file that's weirdly
and historically just called a dot out, and we can see that.
中文字幕
If I click this folder icon up here, you'll
actually see my file hello dot C and another file now called a dot out.
中文字幕
It stands for assembly output, but for historical reasons.
Now let me close the folder icon because we're generally not going
中文字幕
to use the graphical user interface.
How do I run that program?
中文字幕
I couldn't just double click on the icon.
This isn't a Mac.
中文字幕
This isn't a PC.
This is a cloud based Linux environment.
中文字幕
Linux is a super popular operating system.
It happens to be used by lots of computer scientists, lots of websites,
中文字幕
lots of servers.
In fact, almost every website you visit these days is powered,
中文字幕
if not by Windows by Linux, and variations thereof
called Unix and other flavors still.
中文字幕
It's just a very popular and often free operating system
that CS50 Sandbox itself uses.
中文字幕
To run a file called a dot out that's in this folder, so to speak,
even though you don't see a graphical version of it.
中文字幕
You literally just type dot slash a dot out.
Completely non-obvious and kind of a stupid name for the program,
中文字幕
but this is the equivalent in your Mac or PC of double clicking on an icon.
Let me go ahead and hit enter.
中文字幕
And when I do, I should hopefully see what?
Hello world.
中文字幕
And here we go.
Wow, that's our first program.
中文字幕
It's not doing all that much, but it's at least
doing what we promised it would do.
中文字幕
And this is the equivalent in Scratch of just saying on the screen hello world.
Now to be fair, there were more steps involved,
中文字幕
and God knows there was more cryptic looking code to write.
But at the end of the day all we've done now
中文字幕
is re-implement last week's logic in this new language,
but we're now going to very quickly introduce new puzzle pieces but in C.
中文字幕
But first let's solve this minor headache.
I don't really want to tell friends like,
中文字幕
hey, everyone, come run my a dot out program.
Let's give it a real name.
中文字幕
Suppose I just want to call my program hello
like you might download from the App Store or Google Play Store.
中文字幕
Programs have names.
So how do I do that?
中文字幕
Well, it turns out in a terminal window, the so-called command line environment,
which is just a fancy way of saying you write lines of commands
中文字幕
with your keyboard, you can actually pass
in what are called command line arguments, additional inputs
中文字幕
to programs that are just words that you type at your keyboard that tell it
how to behave.
中文字幕
So instead of just running clang on hello dot
C, I'm actually going to be more explicit
中文字幕
and I'm going to tell clang please output--
as is implied by literally typing dash 0 for output--
中文字幕
a file called hello instead.
So it's a little more verbose--
中文字幕
hello dash O hello-- or, sorry clang dash O hello hello dot C.
But what this is going to do now is still convert
中文字幕
source code to machine code, but it's going
to save it in a file called hello.
中文字幕
And indeed now I have hello dot C a dot out and hello as
pictured in the little graphical folder there.
中文字幕
So now I can instead run dot slash hello.
What should it say?
中文字幕
Hopefully the same, enter.
So that's it.
中文字幕
Those are called command line arguments, and it's just
the old school way of telling a text based command
中文字幕
how to behave a little bit differently from its defaults.
But frankly, this is going to get tedious quickly.
中文字幕
We aren't going to want to write our code
and then every darn time we want to convert it to zeros and ones to run it
中文字幕
actually remember these magical incantations of commands.
And so humans have abstracted these away too.
中文字幕
It turns out that, if you want to make a program from source code
into machine code, there's another command you can use.
中文字幕
And you can literally type make hello, where
hello is the name of the program you want to make,
中文字幕
this program, whose name is make, will look for a file
by default called hello dot C, therefore saving you the time of specifying it.
中文字幕
Hit Enter now, and, oh my god, look what it just did.
It has even more configuration options that are baked into it,
中文字幕
and we as CS50 staff, configured CS50 sandbox to have these various features.
And even though we're not going to go into detail on them now,
中文字幕
I'm going to wave my hand at what they actually do.
They just make additional features possible that we'll eventually get to.
中文字幕
But this would be otherwise the command that you all
do have to type in just two or three or four weeks time,
中文字幕
and no one can ever remember that.
I certainly couldn't.
中文字幕
So Make just automates that for you.
But when you run Make, Make is not a compiler.
中文字幕
Make is not the thing in the middle here converting source code to machine code.
It's just a second program that some humans wrote years ago that use
中文字幕
clang in an automated way to achieve the same output.
Because people got tired of typing stuff like this.
中文字幕
So someone made a program called Make that does it for us.
Any questions?
中文字幕
Let's add a little bit then to this program.
Instead of this version of hello, let me get some user input
中文字幕
and actually do something with it.
Suppose I actually want to get the user's name and then print that out.
中文字幕
Well, we saw the spoiler for that just a moment ago,
but let me go ahead and add to this program here.
中文字幕
Now I have a second line of code, and I want to get a string from a user.
And with what function do I get a string from the user?
中文字幕
Get string was the one, and recall I can do get
underscore string open parenthesis.
中文字幕
And then I have to pass in an argument, so to speak, like give me your name--
or actually, what did we say before?
中文字幕
What is your name, I think was the prompt backslash n semi-colon.
Now it's not enough to just get the string.
中文字幕
What do I want to do with it?
Yes, store in a variable.
中文字幕
What type of variable?
A string.
中文字幕
So I just need to go on the left hand side of this line of code
and say, OK, well, give me a string.
中文字幕
I'll call it name, but I could call it x or y or anything.
But name feels like a good descriptor for it,
中文字幕
using a single equal sign to copy from right to left.
And now I've got that.
中文字幕
Now it's not sufficient to just store the value in the variable.
I need to print it out.
中文字幕
So let me start with this.
It autosaves, the Sandbox.
中文字幕
So I don't even have to go up to File, Save or anything.
Let me go ahead and do make hello now--
中文字幕
oh uh, oh my god, look at all these errors already.
So clearly something is wrong, as the computer is fond of telling me in red.
中文字幕
And frankly, this is where you very quickly
get derailed or kind of freaked out because,
中文字幕
oh my god, I only wrote two lines of code.
How do I have 20 lines of errors somehow?
中文字幕
So the computer is kind of as confused as you.
And the most important thing, when you face this kind of situation
中文字幕
where it's just cryptic, erroneous output, start at the top.
Even if your window's kind of small and therefore a whole bunch of stuff
中文字幕
scrolls on the screen quickly, scroll up to the top
because odds are there's one mistake up at the very top
中文字幕
and that one mistake just had a cascading effect on the compiler.
Then it just got really confused, and it just kept spitting out messages
中文字幕
because it got tripped up early.
So let's scroll back up to the top here.
中文字幕
And here is the very long command that I said make automates for you.
So that's not erroneous.
中文字幕
Here seems to be the first error, and it's a little cryptic still.
But let's glean some information.
中文字幕
Here's a familiar phrase--
hello dot C. Let me go ahead and zoom in on the bottom here.
中文字幕
So hello dot C recalls the name of my file.
Albeit not obviously, clang is telling me look at line 5 and then
中文字幕
your fifth character.
So this something colon something means line number character or column number
中文字幕
if you're looking from left to right.
Error means error.
中文字幕
And then this is where things get a little sophisticated.
Use of undeclared identifier string--
中文字幕
did you mean standard n?
No I didn't, but I do recognize standard n,
中文字幕
or rather it seems similar to standard I/O. But no, I didn't mean that.
I'm pretty sure this code is right.
中文字幕
Well, why am I getting this error?
It sounds like string, on line five, fifth character, right there,
中文字幕
that is wrong.
Well, it turns out, there is no such thing as a string.
中文字幕
C, the language, has integers, and it has Booleans, it turns out.
And it has characters and a few other things.
中文字幕
It actually doesn't have strings.
Strings is a word that's useful to describe sequences
中文字幕
of characters, paragraphs, words.
But string is not a type.
中文字幕
It's not a type of variable unless you make it so.
And in fact, this is one of the simplifications we do.
中文字幕
In just the first couple of weeks of the course to get us off the ground,
it turns out that we need to add one line of code here.
中文字幕
We need to do, not only include standard I/O-- which we'll explain in a moment--
but also CS50 so-called library.
中文字幕
So CS50 has a lot of humans involved with it, and over time we've decided,
you know what, we could make the first hour of CS50 a little easier
中文字幕
and the on ramp a little cleaner for folks with no background
by just inventing a few features ourselves such as the ability
中文字幕
to get strings from the user.
So it turns out get string is also not a function that
中文字幕
comes with C. That is a custom puzzle piece, so to speak, that CS50 made.
And where we created that function is essentially in a file
中文字幕
called CS50 dot age.
And so by including dot age, you now get access
中文字幕
to more puzzle pieces, if you will, that we have created for you.
And it turns out this line of code that has
中文字幕
been here before is also giving you features, too.
We're just doing what everyone does in programming,
中文字幕
which is solve a problem once and then let other people use that solution.
Take a guess.
中文字幕
What functionality is actually implemented
in a file called standard I/O input output dot h?
中文字幕
This is just a file somewhere on the server that actually does come with C,
and it provides you with handy features like what?
中文字幕
Say again.
Once more.
中文字幕
Printf.
It turns out that the means by which you are allowed to use a function
中文字幕
called printf here is you have to include
the file in which it is declared.
中文字幕
So some humans, years ago, literally wrote a function, a puzzle piece,
called printf, and they figured out how to actually draw
中文字幕
characters on the screen.
They then stored information about that function in a file
中文字幕
called standard IO dot age.
If I had not included that seemingly cryptic line of code
中文字幕
at the very top of my previous program, even that hello world program would not
have worked because clang, the compiler, wouldn't
中文字幕
have known what I'm talking about.
What is printf?
中文字幕
I don't know what that is unless you tell
it to also include this file that humans wrote years
中文字幕
ago in which printf has been created.
And now if I want to use get string, as well as the new keyword string,
中文字幕
I need to tell clang the compiler, also go ahead
and look in CS50.h for more functionality, such as string
中文字幕
and get string.
So let me go ahead now and try this again.
中文字幕
I'm going to clear my terminal here and just try that same command again--
make hello, enter, dammit.
中文字幕
Now I've got another error.
But, but, but, progress.
中文字幕
Well, no, just as many errors as before somehow, but different ones.
Notice now-- wait, that was before.
中文字幕
Oh, no, I'm sorry.
It has fewer errors.
中文字幕
Here's where I ran the command a moment ago,
and now I'm getting this error instead.
中文字幕
So progress.
Now my error is not on line 5.
中文字幕
It's on line 6, though fun fact, line 6 used to be line 5.
So it's apparently still involved in the problem.
中文字幕
So let's read the error message.
The problem is on line 6, which is no surprising is that one there.
中文字幕
But this time it's different-- error, unused variable name.
That one I kind of understand even without being a programmer.
中文字幕
What does that mean?
Yeah.
中文字幕
Maybe declare prior to using, but it turns out this is how you declare it.
But I'm actually-- yeah.
中文字幕
You're not actually using the variable you declared.
Yeah, I'm just kind of wasting the computer's time.
中文字幕
I'm creating it.
So line 6 on the left is correct.
中文字幕
Hey, computer, give me a string variable,
and call it name and put a value in it.
中文字幕
But what's the point of that exercise if you're never,
as you say, doing anything with it.
中文字幕
And in fact, recall from the slide a moment ago,
how do I do something with it?
中文字幕
Well, this is not how you do something with it.
If I go ahead and run this program now successfully,
中文字幕
what would I actually see on the screen?
Literally hello name, H-E-L-L-O comma space N-A-M-E, obviously not correct.
中文字幕
So how do I plug in the variable?
What was the trick?
中文字幕
Yeah, percent S for string, a format code,
so to speak-- hence the name printf.
中文字幕
And then I need to pass a second argument to printf,
and I do that with a comma and then the name of the variable I want to plug in.
中文字幕
Now notice there are two commas in this line here.
If I zoom in, notice there's two commas, but there's only
中文字幕
two arguments or inputs to printf.
The input to a function is just typically called an argument
中文字幕
or also called a parameter.
So there are two commas, but this one is an English comma just separating hello
中文字幕
from the person's name.
This white comma here, color coded because the Sandbox is doing the for me
中文字幕
is actually separating-- excuse me-- the first argument
from the second argument.
中文字幕
So now, for a third time, make hello enter.
Oh my god, thank you.
中文字幕
Now it worked.
It still spit out this pretty long, cryptic command in white,
中文字幕
but that's OK.
That is, again, the automated command that Make is making possible for us.
中文字幕
But the fact that I see no red, no errors, just another blinking prompt
means that my program has been made.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and do--
how do I run a program if it's called hello?
中文字幕
Yeah, dot slash hello, and we'll see why you
have the stupid dot at the beginning.
中文字幕
It essentially means run the program called hello
that's right here in your current folder on the server--
中文字幕
dot slash hello.
What is your name?
中文字幕
Very nice.
David, enter.
中文字幕
Hello, David.
Interesting.
中文字幕
Let's make one tweak, because I did this by accident earlier as you noted.
What if I left off for instance one of these backslash n's
中文字幕
that's literally now not telling the computer
to move the cursor to another line?
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and rerun the program.
Wait a minute.
中文字幕
That looks the same.
I just changed the code, but it's still behaving exactly the same.
中文字幕
Where's my confusion?
I didn't recompile it.
中文字幕
Unlike Scratch, which is amazing because you just hit the green flag
and it runs the code again, we have a second intermediate step.
中文字幕
I have to re-run the code.
Now how do you get out of a program?
中文字幕
I could just hit Enter.
You can also hit Control C for cancel, and that will just get you out
中文字幕
of whatever confusion you're in.
Let me go ahead and rerun, make hello--
中文字幕
seems to be OK--
dot slash hello, enter.
中文字幕
OK, this is why I've had all those backslash n's.
Let me zoom in on what's happening.
中文字幕
I mean, it doesn't look horrible, but frankly it kind of rubs me
the wrong way if this is what my program looks
中文字幕
like when I'm typing in user input.
I mean, this just looks stupid.
中文字幕
Minimally, I should add a space.
Maybe I can put a backslash n to move the character.
中文字幕
This is user interface now.
This isn't really logic.
中文字幕
It's just aesthetics, but I think this looks stupid.
So that's why I've had the backslash n's there all the time,
中文字幕
but that's why they need to be there to tell the computer to actually put
things where you want them.
中文字幕
Alternatively, you know what, OK, I don't like that.
Control-C for cancel.
中文字幕
Let me put this one back.
What happens if I get rid of this one?
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and recompile the code first
as you note dot slash hello enter.
中文字幕
OK, I've cleaned up that aesthetic headache, enter.
I mean, it's not quite the same problem, but this looks stupid too
中文字幕
because the dollar sign just represents my prompt where
I'm supposed to type commands and yet hello comma David prompt.
中文字幕
And that's just messy.
So this is why we've had all of these new lines.
中文字幕
Now you asked earlier, what if you put the new line elsewhere in the string.
Well, suppose I do that.
中文字幕
Suppose I put a couple of them.
Let me do this and no spaces whatsoever.
中文字幕
Now this is looking a little weird, but the computer is just going to interpret
this literally-- print H-E-L-L-O comma new line substitute in the string
中文字幕
for percent S then another new line.
So how many lines of output is this going to display?
中文字幕
I heard four.
Other values?
中文字幕
Let's see.
Let's go ahead and make hello and then run
中文字幕
dot slash hello, what is your name as before enter hello comma new line
David-- so four total lines certainly or just two lines from the computer
中文字幕
itself.
So just to recap then, with code like this
中文字幕
how many functions have I used in this particular program?
How many functions?
中文字幕
So it's two-- printf, which we've been using and get
string, which is the new one.
中文字幕
Where is string declared?
CS50 dot h, printf meanwhile is declared in standard IO.h standard input output.
中文字幕
Meanwhile, string, this data type also comes from CS50 itself,
and then we've used the format codes, and we've
中文字幕
use variables to achieve the same result.
And let's just hammer this home.
中文字幕
Brian and Karim, do you mind popping up for just a second?
Or who's there?
中文字幕
Erin, come on up.
So just to make this clear because there is now
中文字幕
some terminology that we want to use.
Let's see.
中文字幕
Do you want to be--
you'll be get string.
中文字幕
So we have some name tags here like you get at events.
So Erin shall be get underscore string.
中文字幕
If you want go ahead and put this on.
And Brian, you want to be printf.
中文字幕
So we won't act out all of our actual programs
because this will quickly become obvious.
中文字幕
So Brian is printf.
So this point though, remains in that this is nice
中文字幕
that I have some colleagues with whom I work here
because I don't really want to do all of the hard work of making things happen.
中文字幕
And so if I'm instead the programmer or the orchestrator
of a whole bunch of things happening, I can actually implement this code now
中文字幕
more physically.
And let's focus, though, for just a moment on what the key takeaways are.
中文字幕
One, functions can take input.
Those inputs are called arguments or parameters,
中文字幕
and functions can return things.
They can have return values.
中文字幕
Printf, for instance, does it take input?
What's the input to printf, for instance?
中文字幕
Yeah, like hello world.
Whatever it is you want to print is by definition the input to printf.
中文字幕
Does print return a value thus far?
It does do something on the screen certainly.
中文字幕
It prints stuff on the screen, but we haven't
seen it return something because we haven't seen it with equal sign
中文字幕
to the left.
Now it turns out printf does return things.
中文字幕
It's just not often that useful to use, but we've only
seen printf for the moment as taking inputs-- more on that another time.
中文字幕
Get string, meanwhile-- does get string take inputs?
How many inputs?
中文字幕
Just one, the prompt that you want the human to see.
The first prompt I used was what is your name.
中文字幕
I could make the prompt anything, but that's
the question that get string is asking.
中文字幕
Does get string return a value?
It does.
中文字幕
That's of course in Scratch called answer, hard coded as answer.
We can store in any variable we want.
中文字幕
So let me just go ahead and implement this program.
Erin, go get me a string and ask the person, what is their name.
中文字幕
So--
ERIN: What is your name?
中文字幕
Elizabeth.
So she's writing down Elizabeth now.
中文字幕
But Erin has taken input from me.
Erin, go get someone's name and ask them, what is their name.
中文字幕
And now you've produce output for me.
Thank you.
中文字幕
This is the return value, storing the value Elizabeth,
and I'm going to go ahead and took it away
中文字幕
in a variable called name like this piece of paper here.
OK, Brian, could you go ahead and say hello Elizabeth.
中文字幕
So what's going on here?
I'm just doing less work.
中文字幕
I am writing this program--
Erin, go get someone's name, Brian, could you print this out.
中文字幕
That's what I've been doing, is programming,
just delegating functionality to other functions or in this case
中文字幕
other humans who know how to do that.
And honestly, I don't have to know how Erin got that name.
中文字幕
She just got it.
I don't have to know how Brian wrote in that particular kind of style
中文字幕
of English on the screen.
I just know that he can do it, and now my program is complete.
中文字幕
Thank you very much to both of these two here.
We'll continue in just a moment as follows.
中文字幕
So all this time, we've been taking for granted
that we have an actual computer on which we can execute code,
中文字幕
and I keep saying Intel inside that's the silly slogan that you see inside
of most Macs and PCs with the hardware they have.
中文字幕
But the CPU is just the brains of the computer.
And at the end of the day, recall that the goal
中文字幕
is to actually have the computer turn something like this--
source code-- into actual machine code, zeros and ones.
中文字幕
And that's all Clang was actually doing for us.
Of course, we've only just scratched the surface now of what we can do.
中文字幕
It turns out there's going to be, not just these
commands that we can run, but other features of C
中文字幕
and in particular the CS50 library.
We've only seen thus far how to get a string,
中文字幕
but you can get integers and characters and funky things
like floats and doubles, which actually open a can of worms
中文字幕
as to problems that can happen in a computer.
And it turns out you can store different types of variables, not just
中文字幕
integers and strings, but bool for Boolean and chars for characters.
And you can format those things in printf.
中文字幕
We've only seen percent S. I alluded to percent i earlier,
but there's a few other still.
中文字幕
But we've got a lot of possibilities here.
But let's go ahead and take, say, a five minute break to give everyone
中文字幕
bit of a respite, turn on some music, and come back in five and dive
in deeper to more sophisticated programs in C.
中文字幕
So recall we began by comparing some Scratch
blocks against the corresponding C code, but we didn't actually
中文字幕
use most of those blocks in C just yet.
So let's try out a number of examples, some of which I'll write on the fly
中文字幕
in typing code out on my own keyboard, some of which
we already have in the course's web sites.
中文字幕
So we can just open them to save some time.
But let me just draw your attention to what
中文字幕
CS50 Sandbox is because this was the step that I skipped over earlier.
CS50 Sandbox can be used to program in bunches of languages.
中文字幕
We'll initially in the semester use it for C.
But if you've written Java before or Python or any number of languages,
中文字幕
when you go to Sandbox.CS50.io, you can simply
choose the language you want to write in.
中文字幕
And then at the bottom, you'll see you can
specify the name of the file you want to precreate.
中文字幕
So for instance, what I did earlier was I selected C at top, and then
at the bottom I typed in Hello dot C because that
中文字幕
was the name of the file I wanted.
And then I clicked start.
中文字幕
And what that led me to was precisely the interface in which we wrote hello
dot C just a moment ago, where my code editor appears on the top here,
中文字幕
my terminal window appears at the bottom,
and then I'm allowed to just start writing code.
中文字幕
So that's how we got to where we were.
And if you want to follow along now with some of these examples,
中文字幕
note that on the course's website we have all of them premade.
And you can actually click the links on the course's web site
中文字幕
and open up your own copy of a sandbox with that code.
So if the Wi-Fi cooperates, you're welcome to tinker and play and run
中文字幕
the same commands.
But everything is also on the course's website after.
中文字幕
So you needn't type everything out.
So let's go ahead and do just a quick example.
中文字幕
I'm going to call this int dot C just so that we can reinforce
some of what we did just a moment ago.
中文字幕
Rather than get a string like we did with our hello example, let me go ahead
and just get, say, an integer, and then print it out
中文字幕
just as we did print a name.
So I'm going to have to go ahead and, just through muscle memory,
中文字幕
I remember that I need standard IO dot h of the top
and then int main void and then curly braces.
中文字幕
And then I can do the act of actually getting the input.
So there was a function before called get string.
中文字幕
It turns out there's another function called
get int if you want to get an integer.
中文字幕
So I can actually call get int, and I can say something
like integer is the prompt.
中文字幕
Like, hey, human, please give me an integer.
I need a semi-colon at the end of this line.
中文字幕
And then how do I actually store the return value of get int in a variable?
Just as Erin handed me a sheet of paper with a string,
中文字幕
I'm handed a sheet of paper with a number, how do I store it somewhere?
What's should I literally type line five here?
中文字幕
Int space and then number or something.
So I'm going to call it i just because it's an integer,
中文字幕
but I could call it number or anything else.
And then I'm going to go ahead and print this out.
中文字幕
So printf-- let's say something like hello i backslash n semi-colon.
Not quite correct, right?
中文字幕
This is going to literally print hello comma.
How do I actually substitute something in?
中文字幕
Well, we've only seen how to substitute in strings,
but I think I spoiled earlier the answer.
中文字幕
If you use percent i, that says, hey, computer, put an integer here.
Then I need a second argument to printf just
中文字幕
as we handed Brian an argument as well.
And I said i.
中文字幕
I want to say i here.
But this program isn't quite correct yet.
中文字幕
It's in a file called int dot C. I've included standard IO dot h.
It's in main, and so what is main?
中文字幕
Well, today were largely going to wave our hands at that.
But int main void is perhaps the most cryptic way
中文字幕
you can say the equivalent of when green flag clicked.
That's all that does, and we'll come back in the weeks
中文字幕
to come as to why it's int, why it's main, why it's void.
But for now, humans years ago just decided
中文字幕
that, when you're writing a program in C and you want to start the program off,
you literally have to type int main void with those parentheses
中文字幕
with those curly braces, and it's the equivalent to Scratch
is when green flag clicked.
中文字幕
But this program will not compile, and I don't even
want to induce the stress of seeing those errors.
中文字幕
How do I void it?
Yeah, I need to teach the computer that get int exists,
中文字幕
and I know how to do that from before by including the CS50 so-called library.
Technically, CS50 dot h is a header file.
中文字幕
Dot h means header, and it's just a file containing C code
in which the functions are created.
中文字幕
More on that another time, but that just gives us access to printf.
So if I've made no typos, I should be able to compile
中文字幕
this program by running what command?
Make int.
中文字幕
I could do Clang.
I could do Clang dash O. But for now I'm going to do it simpler with just
中文字幕
make int and let make automate the process of compiling this program.
No error messages is good.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and zoom in--
dot slash int I think would run the program.
中文字幕
Integer, how about 42?
Hello 42.
中文字幕
And notice, I can save time now.
And if I want to run it again, I don't have to do slash int all the time.
中文字幕
It turns out that in this kind of Linux environment,
this operating system called Linux, you can actually go up and down
中文字幕
and see previous commands you've typed and some others that
happen to be system specific.
中文字幕
And if you just set up and enter, you can run it again, type in 50 this time,
and see another output as well.
中文字幕
So any questions then on just an example like that?
No?
中文字幕
Well, let me go ahead, and I'm going to save time in this environment.
I can actually create files in here if I want by clicking the folder icon,
中文字幕
clicking the plus.
And then I can actually say give me a file called float dot C.
中文字幕
So this is equivalent to going back to the main menu
and typing in the name of the file.
中文字幕
I'm just going to do it a little more quickly
now in this graphical environment.
中文字幕
And I want to call it float dot C.
It's A bit of a weird name because at least growing up you probably
中文字幕
learned maybe about integers.
You probably learned about real numbers, numbers
中文字幕
that can have decimal points and then things after the decimal point.
In a computer, those things with decimal points
中文字幕
are called floating point values, or floats.
And you can think of it as the decimal point can kind of float
中文字幕
to the left or the right, depending on how big or small the number is
or how precise the numbers after the decimal point are.
中文字幕
That's a float.
So let me go ahead and implement a very similar program--
中文字幕
include CS50 dot h include, standard IO h int main void--
and this is after 20 years of doing this that you can do it so quickly.
中文字幕
Now let me instead get a float from the user--
so a real number that may very well have a decimal point in it.
中文字幕
I'm going to do that a little differently.
I'll zoom in, and I'm going to say, hey, computer, give me a float,
中文字幕
as is the data type called--
not int, not string but float.
中文字幕
I'll call it f just because that sounds like float, and it's nice
and succinct-- equals get float.
中文字幕
And then I'm just going to say float.
That's the prompt.
中文字幕
I could make the prompt in green anything I want.
And now I'm going to print it--
中文字幕
printf hello f, but I don't want f.
I want to actually print out a placeholder and you can probably
中文字幕
guess by now what the pattern is--
percent f for a float new line comma f semi-colon.
中文字幕
So this is like the same program three times now with a string, with an int,
and a float.
中文字幕
But again, it's just for some muscle memory and going through the pattern,
but let's see what happens differently here.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and type make float enter.
OK, good, no errors.
中文字幕
Let me zoom in and run this now as dot slash float.
And let me go ahead and type in a number.
中文字幕
I'm going to just say 42.
But the computer now has the capability of storing more precision.
中文字幕
Before it was just an integer by definition of int.
Now it's a float.
中文字幕
So even though it's pretty precise, this 42.0000,
that's indeed a real number now, storing some amount of precision there.
中文字幕
So it turns out though that we can do more interesting math.
Let me go ahead and just open this example in advance.
中文字幕
This one is going to be called int dot C.
So then I don't have to type everything out.
中文字幕
And in ints dot C, we're going to see some math written in code that I
pre-created just to reinforce that you can actually
中文字幕
do some basic arithmetic in a program.
I can make see more of the code here by just scrolling down,
中文字幕
and let me scroll this up so we can focus on main.
And let me zoom in on the first few lines.
中文字幕
On this first line, I'm just getting an int, and I'm calling it x.
We've not used a variable called x recently.
中文字幕
But now we are.
It's no different logically than before.
中文字幕
Here get me another variable.
So we can see now that you can get multiple variables from the user
中文字幕
just like in Scratch.
And now in these lines, in green are just some format
中文字幕
strings-- just what do I want printf to display?
I literally, in this highlighted line here, want printf to display x plus y
中文字幕
equals something.
What is that something?
中文字幕
Well, notice what's cool about printf is that, before it is passed in input,
you can perform simple arithmetic operations.
中文字幕
So if you want to add x and y together, literally do x plus y.
Then the sum of those numbers is what will get handed to printf as its input.
中文字幕
Just like I handed Erin's piece of paper to Brian as input,
I'm handing not x and y to Brian in this case, but x plus y
中文字幕
or some value, the actual sum.
Similarly, subtraction is the hyphen on your keyboard.
中文字幕
For multiplication, it's not an x.
That would be weird, xxy.
中文字幕
It's instead star, or an asterisk on your keyboard.
Division is the single slash, and then this one is a little funky,
中文字幕
but we'll come up with some uses for this.
You can actually do modular arithmetic or just more simply remainders.
中文字幕
If you do x percent y, you'll get back the remainder of dividing x by y.
And what's the remainder?
中文字幕
So if x is 20 and y is 10, well, 20 divided by 10 goes in twice perfectly.
So remainder is 0, for instance.
中文字幕
But it's been a while.
So notice, though, what's curious here.
中文字幕
In this context, percent is not a placeholder.
It's not percent S. It's not percent i.
中文字幕
It's not percent Notice it's not inside of printf's format string.
This is just literally math, a math operator
中文字幕
as is implied by the different color blue there.
So if I actually run this--
中文字幕
let's go ahead and run this program.
I'm going to go ahead and do our make ints--
中文字幕
plural because that's the name of the file--
enter dot slash ints.
中文字幕
And let me zoom in and clear the screen.
Enter.
中文字幕
Give me a number.
2 I heard.
中文字幕
And another.
10 I heard.
中文字幕
So FYI, 2 plus 10 is 12, 2 minus 10 is negative 8, 2 times 10 is 20,
2 divided by 10 is--
中文字幕
2 mod y, or 2 and then take the remainder when dividing by y
is what mod means is 2.
中文字幕
So I get four out of five for correctness?
What's a little funky here?
中文字幕
Yeah, 2 divided by 10?
Like, I'm pretty sure that's like 2/10 or maybe one fifth or 0.2.
中文字幕
I mean, I'll take any number of answers but not 0.
So what's going on?
中文字幕
Well, this is a matter of representation.
It turns out in a computer program, we decided
中文字幕
in advance I'm going to store ints.
An int is something that does not have a decimal point.
中文字幕
And yet here I am rather presumptuously trying
to do to 2, an integer, divided by 10, an integer,
中文字幕
and expecting something other than an integer.
No, I literally am doing integer arithmetic.
中文字幕
So what's the computer apparently doing just intuitively?
Why, when dividing x by y as I did in this line here--
中文字幕
or specifically in this example you proposed, 2 divide by 10--
where is my 2/10 going?
中文字幕
Yeah, it's technically what?
Supposed to be 0.2, or 0.2.
中文字幕
That's actually the solution because, if it's 0.2 but integers
can't store decimal points or anything after them, what do you have left?
中文字幕
Just the zero at the beginning.
So integer arithmetic is fine if you're working with integers,
中文字幕
but if you want floating point arithmetic,
you're going to need to make some changes.
中文字幕
And so I can fix this.
In fact, let me go ahead and write a different program here.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up from the course's website
floats dot C. That's going to give me this example, which is implemented
中文字幕
using floating point values instead.
So once this loads, I'm going to see a program I wrote in advance.
中文字幕
It's a little shorter because now I only care about looking at one problem.
And notice now x and y are now floats and not ints,
中文字幕
another data type that exists.
And I'm using get float, which also comes from CS50's library.
中文字幕
And then this line is almost the same, but you know what?
Let me let me tweak this.
中文字幕
Let me just make it exactly the same.
This line now that I've highlighted is exactly the same as before.
中文字幕
So if I do type in the same number--
so let's go ahead and zoom in and do make floats plural and dot slash
中文字幕
floats.
I'll give it 2 and 10, and I should hopefully see what now?
中文字幕
0.2.
That's pretty good, pretty precise.
中文字幕
But you know what?
I hate to tell you, but let's look a little farther.
中文字幕
It turns out by default, when you percent
f, you only see a few decimal places, like five or so it looks, by default.
中文字幕
Let me see a few more so.
This was one one, two, three, four, five, six
中文字幕
points after the decimal point.
So you know what?
中文字幕
I'm going to say, hey, computer, give me decimal points.
This looks completely cryptic and you just
中文字幕
have to kind of remember this or look it up if you forget.
If you put a dot and a number in between the percent and the f,
中文字幕
that's the cryptic way of telling the computer show
me a float but with this many decimal places, please.
中文字幕
So that just gives me decimal places, weird as the expression looks.
Now hopefully I'm just going to see some more zeros.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and make floats, and let me go ahead
and zoom in and do dot slash floats 2 10 enter.
中文字幕
OK, still correct.
Let me get a little curious.
中文字幕
Let's see a lot of zeros, like 50 of them.
Let me go down here and do make floats, because I changed the code,
中文字幕
dot slash floats 2 10.
Ha, your grade school teachers lied to you.
中文字幕
2 divided by 10 is apparently not 0.2000000 infinitely.
It's apparently 0.20000000298023223876953125 and then
中文字幕
all of those zeros.
What the hell is going on?
中文字幕
Where's the bug?
Where's my mistake?
中文字幕
Where's my misunderstanding?
What's the explanation for this?
中文字幕
Well, what if I told you that inside of your computer is stuff like this?
This is RAM or memory, and you've probably generally known this idea.
中文字幕
They just store files.
They store music and videos.
中文字幕
You need memory, some kind of space.
Hard disk space is permanent storage.
中文字幕
RAM, or Random Access Memory, is temporary storage.
So when your laptop is open and your desktop computers is on
中文字幕
or your phone is powered, you're using RAM for all of the programs
you're running at once.
中文字幕
If you open a file, that file is stored in RAM,
but it's permanently stored on your hard drive.
中文字幕
So there's different types of memory.
But notice, this is zoomed in.
中文字幕
In reality, this is like couple of inches wide and maybe an inch tall.
So it's pretty small, but it doesn't really matter how big it is.
中文字幕
It just matters that it's finite in size.
You have physical hardware on your laps or in your pockets or at home
中文字幕
that only are so big and therefore only have so many parts
and therefore only have so many transistors
中文字幕
and other pieces of hardware that's actually
doing the work of storing information.
中文字幕
And so if you only have a finite amount of memory, how in the world
are we going to represent an infinite number of numbers?
中文字幕
Because I do recall from grade school I was
taught there is an infinite number of numbers, certainly real numbers, where
中文字幕
the decimal point can go on forever.
That is a problem if you want to represent all possible numbers
中文字幕
in the universe, which is infinitely many, with a finite amount of hardware.
So at some point, the computer's gotta start cutting some corners.
中文字幕
And so what you're really seeing here is as close
as the computer can get to storing that fraction for you precisely,
中文字幕
and I got a little greedy.
I looked a little too far to the right.
中文字幕
And granted, these are infinitesimally small values.
It's not hugely, hugely off, but it is off
中文字幕
because they can't expect the computer to represent
an infinite number of values using a finite amount of memory.
中文字幕
It's got to round off here or there and be imprecise, so to speak.
So is this a problem?
中文字幕
I mean, we would never have known this if I hadn't gotten greedy
and looked at 50 decimal places instead of 7, which was already pretty precise.
中文字幕
Is this a problem?
Yeah, like why?
中文字幕
Why?
If you use the equal function, [INAUDIBLE]..
中文字幕
Yeah, that's a good one.
Logically, if I start using equals equals to compare things for equality,
中文字幕
it's going to be really hard for me to ever compare something for 2/10
as it's value because I'm going to literally have
中文字幕
to remember or write down or figure out this value and compare against that
and not just compare more loosely against 0.2.
中文字幕
And that's true, you should actually never compare floating point values
in code for equality.
中文字幕
I could probably get away with less than or greater than,
but even then it's going to be a little off from what I expect.
中文字幕
Why else might this imprecision be worrisome?
When might you not want your computer being imprecise?
中文字幕
What domains?
What worlds outside of a classroom?
中文字幕
Yeah?
What's that?
中文字幕
Rocket.
Yeah, so rockets, or anything involving math and physics and danger.
中文字幕
You don't want numbers to be ever so slightly off.
And if you think about it, rockets is a good example
中文字幕
because I don't know much about rockets, but I know they go pretty fast
and there's probably angles involved because you're
中文字幕
trying to keep them on a trajectory.
And that's fine.
中文字幕
But if your trajectory is ever so slightly off
and something's going really fast and really far,
中文字幕
I'm pretty sure that eventually those small imprecisions start to add up.
And indeed, there's been historical incidents
中文字幕
where that kind of imprecision does, in fact, add up
in the realm of militaristic operations or in financial operations.
中文字幕
In fact, if you've ever seen Office Space or way back when Superman 3,
this is how some people made some money because they just
中文字幕
kept all of the fractions of pennies that computer systems were just
ignoring.
中文字幕
And eventually, they start to add up.
So long story short, any time you have scientific or financial
中文字幕
or any sort of large data sets that involve big numbers and lots of them
and lots of time, this is a problem.
中文字幕
And it almost suggests you shouldn't you C or let alone computers
unless we actually address this.
中文字幕
Now as a spoiler, humans have chipped away at this problem,
and you can use more and more bits but not infinitely many bits.
中文字幕
At some point you have to draw a line, but this
is why, for instance, a stock exchange might only
中文字幕
represent two decimal points of precision
for dollars or maybe four decimal points to the thousandths place for dollars
中文字幕
and cents.
And they just have to decide, that's all the precision
中文字幕
we can actually store precisely.
But you've got to decide how to handle it and not just ignore the problem.
中文字幕
But we can do a little better.
You know what?
中文字幕
It turns out that in most computers a float,
it takes up, yes, a finite amount of space,
中文字幕
but very specifically 32 bits of space or 4 bytes.
A byte, recall, is 8 bits.
中文字幕
So 4 bytes is 32 bits, and that's just a very common unit of measure.
But there's another one.
中文字幕
It turns out, if you want twice as many bits,
you can literally use a data type called double.
中文字幕
And in the CS50 Library, there is a function called get double.
And if I go ahead and do it here, I can now recompile this code,
中文字幕
make floats, even though they're not technically float types anymore.
And let me go ahead and do dot slash floats enter,
中文字幕
and let me type in 2 and 10.
And now it's still imprecise.
中文字幕
But notice, instead of seven zeros, which I think I had before,
now I've got 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15 zeros.
中文字幕
So I've kind of pushed the problem further out, so to speak,
so it's more precise.
中文字幕
But it's not perfect.
You can't get certain values perfect if you
中文字幕
want to be able to represent an infinite range.
Any questions then about this?
中文字幕
And we'll come back as to some implications.
Yeah, here.
中文字幕
So would it always be better if you
use doubles because it's more precise?
中文字幕
Good question.
Would always be better to use doubles because they're more precise?
中文字幕
Short answer, yes, but we're going to see thematically in this course
and computer science more generally there's always a trade-off.
中文字幕
And yes, if you use a double, you will avoid this problem a bit more,
but what price will you pay, so to speak?
中文字幕
Maybe processing power because it's got to deal with more bits at once,
and even more literally, more space.
中文字幕
I mean, sure we can take your solution, but I'm
going to charge you twice as many bits.
中文字幕
And back in the day, decades ago, when C was first being invented
and computers were really coming into play, spending twice as many bits,
中文字幕
even if it's only 32 more tiny zeros and ones,
that was actually expensive literally financially, and it adds up.
中文字幕
And even today, if you want to spend more space,
that's fine, but you're going to spend.
中文字幕
More space, therefore more money, and therefore
have less space available for other things.
中文字幕
So it's just a trade-off.
And you have to decide, as an intelligent human,
中文字幕
where the right inflection point is between what's more important.
Let me open up a very different example now called parity, just as an example.
中文字幕
And let me ask this d how do you know if a number is even or odd?
What's the trick?
中文字幕
Yeah, if it's divided by 2-- so 0 and 2 and 4 and 6
are even because, if you divide by 2, you don't get a remainder.
中文字幕
So actually, if you just want to see a quick example of why
you might use a remainder, even though it's out of context.
中文字幕
Here's an example for parity.
Parity is just a term referring to even or odd in this context.
中文字幕
How might we use this?
Well, notice I can get an int from the user up at the top.
中文字幕
I can then check the parity of the integer-- is it even
or odd-- with syntax like this.
中文字幕
Now I'm combining some of these operators
as you might be inclined intuitively.
中文字幕
If n, the number user typed in, mod 2, or divided by
and then check the remainder of, but that's a mouthful equals equals 0,
中文字幕
you just said it's an even number--
so print even else print odd.
中文字幕
Because what's the possible other remainder?
If you do n or any value divided by 2, you might get a remainder of 0 or 1.
中文字幕
I only have to check for one of those, 0 because the else implies
the other thing.
中文字幕
So again, very simple example.
But honestly, all of us probably have an intuitive understanding
中文字幕
of what's even and odd.
A computer needs to be taught that, and so there's
中文字幕
a program that does exactly that.
Let me open up a larger program called conditions,
中文字幕
and rather than type this one out, because it's a few lines of code,
let me just open it up because it concludes
中文字幕
exactly the code we saw a little bit ago on the slide
when we compared it to a similar C block.
中文字幕
In this program, in my main function-- let me focus on the first few lines
there--
中文字幕
I have an int called x that I'm getting via get int,
another int called y that I'm getting via get int,
中文字幕
and then I'm just doing some simple comparisons.
We saw this again when we compared it to Scratch,
中文字幕
but this is quite simply that same code in context
rather than just seeing it statically on a slide.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and compile this-- make conditions enter.
It seems to compile.
中文字幕
Let me zoom in and do dot slash conditions enter.
x will be, say, 2 again, y will be 10.
中文字幕
x is indeed less than y.
If I run it again-- and I can save time by hitting up through my history
中文字幕
and just hitting Enter.
Let's do 2 and 2, and indeed x is equal to y and so forth.
中文字幕
So again, just the exact same kind of code as before but now
in the context of a working program.
中文字幕
What if I actually wanted to get user input kind of like our past student did
with getting a yes or no answers to the apple and the cupcake question?
中文字幕
Well in answer dot C, it turns out you can actually
get textual input from the user, perhaps a simple yes or no or just y
中文字幕
or n for succinctness.
And in this case, if I just get back a single character,
中文字幕
it turns out there's a separate data type for character.
If you don't want a whole string, like a whole word
中文字幕
or a paragraph or sentence or whatever, you just want one character.
You can actually use what's called a char or character.
中文字幕
And so here I'm using one other function appropriately named called get char.
I'm storing it in a variable called C because it's nice and succinct of type
中文字幕
char, and then notice this.
You might not have seen this syntax before,
中文字幕
especially if you've never programmed before even in Scratch.
But you might have seen this block similar to this in Scratch.
中文字幕
What does the vertical double bar probably imply here?
Or, that's it.
中文字幕
So in Scratch, it's nice and user friendly.
They literally just say O-R. In programming, it's
中文字幕
often the case that use just more cryptic sequences of characters
and two vertical bars, which are typically
中文字幕
above the Enter key on a US keyboard.
If C equals equals capital y or C equals equals lowercase y--
中文字幕
let's assume that the user wanted to say yes and go ahead and say yes.
Else if the user typed in n in capitals or and in lowercase,
中文字幕
let's assume he or she meant no and say no accordingly.
And what are we going to do otherwise?
中文字幕
Apparently nothing, and that's fine.
You don't need to have a default case if you want the program to do nothing.
中文字幕
It might be a little confusing because the user can type in some random word
and get no output, but that's a design decision.
中文字幕
Logically this is just how we might express this.
What about actually building our own blocks?
中文字幕
Any questions, though, before we start to create?
So recall that in Scratch we had that cough example.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and create a file here real quickly
called cough zero dot C and just kind of recreate what we did last week.
中文字幕
Include standard IO dot h int main void--
again, just muscle memory now--
中文字幕
and then printf quote unquote "cough" backslash n semi-colon.
And you know what?
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and cough not once, but twice, three times.
The moment you start copying and pasting,
中文字幕
you're probably not writing good code.
It's not very maintainable.
中文字幕
Now if I want to change the word or translate it to another language,
I have to change it in three places.
中文字幕
We already decided last week that was bad.
So what would be better in C or in Scratch or in general
中文字幕
than this approach?
Yeah, so a for loop.
中文字幕
So let me do that let me create another file.
I'm going to call this one cough one dot C, is my second version.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead now and just copy and paste the original code,
and let's just improve it.
中文字幕
Let's get rid of two of these, and let's see if we can't express the 4.
So it was 4--
中文字幕
let me zoom in--
int i get 0.
中文字幕
i is less than some number.
Before it was 50.
中文字幕
Now I'm going to have it be 3.
i plus plus curly braces, and now let me move the cough block inside of there
中文字幕
and indent it just to be pretty.
And notice stylistically, I've been doing this instinctively for some time.
中文字幕
Everything's nicely indented just to make it more readable,
quite like the Scratch blocks, even though again a lot of white space
中文字幕
doesn't matter to the computer.
So if I go ahead and run this--
中文字幕
let me pull up the terminal window so I can see it.
Make cough one, enter--
中文字幕
looks good-- dot slash cough one cough cough cough.
That's good, but recall that we actually improved this design further
中文字幕
by abstracting it away.
Let me go ahead and make my own function now.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up a new file, cough 2
dot C, just like I had another scratch program.
中文字幕
Again, include standard IO dot h int main void, and then in here
let me go ahead and do what?
中文字幕
Well, for int i get 0, i less than 3, i plus plus plus curly braces.
Then let me go ahead and just call cough.
中文字幕
It would be nice if cough existed, but unfortunately cough does not exist.
It's not in the CS50 library even.
中文字幕
So that's not going to help us.
I have to make my own function.
中文字幕
So in Scratch, you went to the block's thing
and you make your own block and the big prompt comes up
中文字幕
and you make your new puzzle piece.
Here we're going to have to be a little more deliberate,
中文字幕
and it turns out you can do it like this.
Some of these details will be non-obvious at first,
中文字幕
but I'm going to go ahead and call the function cough.
And cough at the moment does not need to take any inputs.
中文字幕
So the key word there is void.
And we've actually seen that before.
中文字幕
Main also has not been taking any inputs.
That's why we had the word void, but more on that another time.
中文字幕
And cough is not going to return anything either.
It's going to print on the screen just like Brian did.
中文字幕
But Brian, recall, didn't hand me anything back physically.
So there's no return value.
中文字幕
So I'm going to say void to the left of cough.
So for today's purposes, this just means that cough neither takes
中文字幕
input nor returns a value as output.
That's it, void, void.
中文字幕
Now as the body of that function, so to speak,
I'm just going to go ahead and say quite simply cough backslash n semi-colon.
中文字幕
That's it.
So now I have a puzzle piece, if you will, whose purpose in life
中文字幕
is to cough, which means now I can magically just call it by its name
up here as many times as I want.
中文字幕
So let's go ahead and compile this.
I'm really on a good roll.
中文字幕
Everything's been working out great so far-- make cough 2, enter, red errors.
So this is interesting, and this kind of reminds me of the previous error.
中文字幕
So first of all, what line is my error on?
Seven and character nine, if you care, but it's seven, on line seven--
中文字幕
implicit declaration of function cough is invalid in C99.
C99 is referring to literally 1999 when this version of C was invented,
中文字幕
and so implicit declaration of function cough.
But it's right here.
中文字幕
OK, wait a minute.
Instinct, let me just move this.
中文字幕
Let me just put it up top.
Let's see what happens.
中文字幕
Make cough 2-- oh my god.
That fixed it.
中文字幕
Why?
Even if you've never programmed before, reason through intuitively
中文字幕
why this solved something.
You are holding a function that you
中文字幕
have had been declared previously.
So even though you are making it void, you at least have [INAUDIBLE]..
中文字幕
Exactly.
Because I previously was trying to use cough early on line 7,
中文字幕
but I was only teaching the computer what cough
was farther down in the file.
中文字幕
Frankly C is kind of dumb.
It literally reads your code top to bottom left or right.
中文字幕
And if you try to do something before you've taught the computer how
to do that, you're going to get that kind of undeclared identifier
中文字幕
because it just doesn't know what the word is yet.
Now in Scratch, this isn't a big deal.
中文字幕
You just move the puzzle pieces anywhere you want.
Order of blocks physically on the screen does not matter.
中文字幕
But in C, it does.
But frankly, this seems a little annoying
中文字幕
that now the main program here keeps getting pushed farther and farther
down the more kind of complexity I want to add to my program.
中文字幕
So there's another solution.
Let me actually go ahead and put this back where
中文字幕
it is because I'm a little particular.
I just like by convention main to be at the top, and frankly that's good style.
中文字幕
If main is the most important function in your program by default--
because it is the main function and it's what gets called per earlier by default
中文字幕
by the computer--
why am I going to push it all the way down just
中文字幕
to work around this stupid detail?
Well, I just need to teach the computer what the function is,
中文字幕
and I can do that a little redundantly by just saying this.
This is what we're going to call the prototype for a function.
中文字幕
If you literally just copy the very first line
of it that has its name, its inputs if any, and its output if any,
中文字幕
that's a prototype semi-colon.
It's literally copy paste from the function itself,
中文字幕
but this is now enough of a hint to say, hey, computer, this shell exists.
This is enough information for you to then call it because the computer,
中文字幕
so long as ir has seen the function's name before, it's
OK if the zeros and ones, so to speak, that implement it come a little later.
中文字幕
And so that's the more conventional way to solve that problem.
So just intuitively then, take a guess, if it's not
中文字幕
too much of a indirect leap, what is in standard I/O h, what is in CS50 dot h.
Those kinds d we'll call them declarations.
中文字幕
So literally in standard IO dot h is a line of code that
teaches the computer what printf's inputs are
中文字幕
and what printf's output is if any.
In CS50 dot h, there is literally a line of code
中文字幕
that tells the computer what get strings input is and what its output is.
And the same for get int and get float and get char and others--
中文字幕
that's all that's in those header files.
The zeros and ones, so to speak, are actually
中文字幕
in files literally called standard IO dot C and CS50 dot C,
although that's technically source code.
中文字幕
The zeros and ones are in a compiled file elsewhere on the system.
But all of these things we've been taking for granted,
中文字幕
now hopefully it makes a little more sense
because, the fact that I'm doing the sharp
中文字幕
include at the top, that's just a solution to a problem.
In that file is enough information to teach the computer what's printf
中文字幕
or what get string and other things are so
that I don't need to bother moving things around myself
中文字幕
or copying and pasting whoever wrote printf, his or her code,
into my program.
中文字幕
Now let's do one final example with coughing
and go ahead and call this call this cough 3 dot C
中文字幕
and go ahead and paste my same code as a moment ago just to get us started.
And recall that the last step of our cough example
中文字幕
last week was to actually give cough an input.
I'd kind of like to whittle this code down
中文字幕
to literally cough 3 because this is a really nice abstraction.
I don't want main to have to think about how many times--
中文字幕
just cough three times.
That's a nice, useful human abstraction.
中文字幕
Now let's put the functionality down here.
So if I want cough to be able to tolerate
中文字幕
an input like 3, which mentions of void presumably needs to change?
The one on the left or the right?
中文字幕
The right, the one inside the parentheses.
And it turns out, just like you can declare variables inside of a function,
中文字幕
as we've done, so can you declare arguments to a function like this.
So you can call it anything you want, though the data type matters, but this
中文字幕
is now saying, hey, computer, cough does not return a value,
like Erin did return a piece of paper.
中文字幕
Hey, computer, cough does take one input.
It's an integer and just call it n.
中文字幕
And now that you've done this, now you can have a line of code in here
like this.
中文字幕
For int i get 0, i is less than n i plus plus--
and then, OK, off by keystrokes here.
中文字幕
Then I can move this inside here, indent it nicely.
And now notice, all of the complexity of coughing
中文字幕
has been factored out into a function, my own puzzle piece,
if you will, that even takes an argument so that now you can literally,
中文字幕
if I move this far away and out of mind, now
your program is getting pretty interesting because it really
中文字幕
just does what it says.
And this is a nice functional abstraction, if you will,
中文字幕
so that now I have a new verb, a new action, a new function called cough.
Any questions on that one?
中文字幕
Yeah.
Sorry, say again.
中文字幕
What integer would main return?
It turns out we'll come back to this.
中文字幕
It's going to return 0 almost always by default,
but that leaves you with almost an infinite number of non-zero values
中文字幕
which represent all of the many things that can go wrong.
So more on that when we start creating more mistakes.
中文字幕
Let's look at one other.
Let me go ahead and open this file in advance
中文字幕
myself called positive dot C. Suppose that I'm not
content to just have access to get int.
中文字幕
I want a function called get positive int because,
for whatever reason, my program, my game,
中文字幕
my whatever needs to know a positive value.
Maybe I'm asking the user how many players are there,
中文字幕
and that shouldn't be negative.
It should be a positive integer like one or two or more.
中文字幕
So it turns out I could write a program if I want that looks like this.
Call on this line here a function called get positive int, pass it in a prompt,
中文字幕
and then store the value, still in an integer, on the left hand side,
and then just go ahead and print it out.
中文字幕
Get positive int has this prototype at the top of the file.
Notice this is not a function that comes with CS50s library, CS50 dot h.
中文字幕
The function is called get positive int.
As you would hope, it returns an int, and it takes a string
中文字幕
as it's prompt, whatever words you want the human to see.
Let's scroll down now, and this one looks a little more involved,
中文字幕
and this is not a feature that Scratch has.
But let's take a look.
中文字幕
The first line is identical to the prototype
because I literally copied and pasted it.
中文字幕
Everything between these brackets is the function itself.
And here, to answer someone's question from earlier on,
中文字幕
do you have to declare a variable and then use it right away?
No, and that's actually a helpful solution to a problem
中文字幕
that we'll see in a moment.
Notice here this new keyword-- didn't see it before--
中文字幕
do the following while n is less than 1.
Previously, we saw a while loop and we saw a for loop.
中文字幕
We did not see a do while loop.
And a do while loop, while it sounds obviously similar to a while
中文字幕
loop, what seems a little different?
When I had that forever block earlier translated to while true,
中文字幕
what was the order of operations?
Did we check the condition, the true, and then print hello world?
中文字幕
Or did we just print hello world and then check the condition?
Yeah, you might not recall precisely, but I did actually--
中文字幕
I checked is true true, and we all said yes obviously.
Printf-- is it true?
中文字幕
Printf-- so it checked the condition first.
You might infer then this loop is a little different.
中文字幕
It has another word, do.
This is literally going to do this first and then check the condition
中文字幕
and only do it again if the condition is true.
So it's a nice way of just flipping things around in terms of order
中文字幕
to do something at least once rather than potentially never at all
like was the case earlier.
中文字幕
So what are we doing?
Get an int, passing in this prompt, store it in n.
中文字幕
And if the user types in a value that's less than 1,
is this going to be true or false, if n is less than 1?
中文字幕
So if the human types in 0, is 0 less than 1?
True, yes, so what happens, you go back to the do and you do it again.
中文字幕
If the user types in negative 1, is negative 1 less than 1?
Yes or true.
中文字幕
So you do it again.
If he or she types in negative 2, again, again.
中文字幕
What if he or she types in 50?
Well, 50 is not less than one.
中文字幕
So this is false.
And so then you proceed to the next line of code altogether.
中文字幕
But what's interesting about the next line of code
is that, unlike the cough example, which had void as its return type,
中文字幕
get positive int by default it's supposed to return an int,
just like, again, Erin handed me a piece of paper with a string on it.
中文字幕
And so here, if I want my own custom function called
get positive int to return value, there's
中文字幕
another word in C. You literally write return and then
the name of the variable or the value that you
中文字幕
want to hand back on a metaphorical piece of paper to whatever code
is using this.
中文字幕
So what's this oddity?
Why can I not do this?
中文字幕
If I were to mimic the code we wrote earlier like this,
why does this line of code not work just logically using
中文字幕
some of the mental models that we've had thus far?
Declaring the code again.
中文字幕
Say again.
Declaring again and again.
中文字幕
Yeah, so declaring just means creating,
is the fancy way in programming of saying creating.
中文字幕
So this says, hey, computer, give me an integer, call it n,
and set it equal to the return value of get int.
中文字幕
So whatever the function or Erin hands me back, put it over here.
But the problem is that in C variables have scope.
中文字幕
Scope is a fancy way of saying they only exist in
between the curly braces between which they were declared.
中文字幕
So that means that this variable n literally only
exists between here and here, and then it just kind of goes away.
中文字幕
The computer doesn't know about it anymore.
But that's a problem because, on what line number
中文字幕
do we actually need to know n?
It looks like 21, and that's outside the curly braces.
中文字幕
So just based on that basic definition, scope
is the two curly braces between which a variable is declared.
中文字幕
It doesn't exist outside of them.
This code just won't work.
中文字幕
And I'll fix it later so that you see the correct error message.
Why does this not work?
中文字幕
Well, you're declaring n inside of those curly braces.
So how do you avoid this?
中文字幕
Well, it turns out, as someone posited earlier, just declare it by itself
without even giving it a value.
中文字幕
And indeed the syntax for that is just to do half of a thought--
int n semi-colon.
中文字幕
It has no value that we know yet.
It has a garbage value, but more on that another time.
中文字幕
But it does now exist.
And now notice which curly braces does it exist within--
中文字幕
this one and this one, which means now it's accessible everywhere.
And if you in your Scratch programs actually used variables,
中文字幕
you might have noticed that you had to choose.
You had to make a decision for this sprite or for all sprites.
中文字幕
That was an allusion to what's called in programming a local
or a global variable.
中文字幕
These are still local, and we'll come back to this term earlier.
But it has to do with scope because, if you had specified for this sprite only,
中文字幕
MIT would have only let you use that variable for that specific sprite,
that cat or sheep or whatever it was you were programming.
中文字幕
Just as in C, this now means n can be used here and here
but not elsewhere like higher up in my program.
中文字幕
That's the matter of scope.
So let's now see what can go wrong beyond that.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up this because it turns out,
when programming, there is other issues that can happen,
中文字幕
not just floating point in precision, as I described it as earlier.
It turns out that there's other problems that can go wrong even with integers
中文字幕
that we kind of avoided altogether.
So recall that we started talking about 1, 2, and 3 and why it's 123 last week.
中文字幕
Well, what happens in decimal if you add 1 to 123?
What number do you get?
中文字幕
Obviously, 124.
If we do it again, 125, 26 27, 28, 29.
中文字幕
What happens in decimal if I add 1 to a 9?
Well, I should get 10, but that's not how we would write this.
中文字幕
You put down the 0 instead, and you carry the 1.
Remember those mental heuristics?
中文字幕
So that's all we did there.
And then it's 2 plus 1.
中文字幕
So that's why 129 plus 1 is 130 because you put the 0, you carry the 1,
and so forth.
中文字幕
So we just all do that intuitively now.
But this has implications for what computers do too
中文字幕
because suppose that we consider a bigger number like 999.
And so what do you get when you add 1 to 999?
中文字幕
Well, you carry the 1, you carry the 1, and you get hopefully 1,000.
But what if your computer only has space for three digits?
中文字幕
Or what if your phone or what if your alarm clock
or whatever the device is literally only has
中文字幕
room for 3 digits, what is 999 plus 1 if your hardware only has three digits?
Well, it's apparently 0.
中文字幕
So you get this overflow 998, 999, 0.
It overflows, so to speak.
中文字幕
The one kind of falls off conceptually, and you roll over to the next value,
which is 000.
中文字幕
So what about in binary?
What number is this in binary if you translated the decimal in your head?
中文字幕
And remember, it's the ones column, the twos columns, and the fours column.
So this was 7 in binary--
中文字幕
1, so it's 4 plus 2 plus 1, so 7 in binary.
So how do you do arithmetic with binary?
中文字幕
It's actually the same thing.
It's just you don't have twos or threes or nines or anything in between.
中文字幕
You just have ones and zeros.
So what do you get when you add 1 to 111?
中文字幕
Well, it's the same idea.
You put down a 0 and you carry the 1 because 1 plus 1
中文字幕
you want to say 2 in decimal, but there is no 2.
So it rolls over to 0.
中文字幕
But you carry the 1.
1 plus 1 is 2, but, OK, that's 0, carry the 1.
中文字幕
1 plus 1, that's 2.
But I don't have a 2.
中文字幕
So I go back to 0, carry the 1.
So in binary, if you only have three bytes or bits rather,
中文字幕
if you only have three bits, what do you get when you add 1 to 7 in binary?
You apparently get 0.
中文字幕
And now it's getting more real.
In my computer, in my phone, in all of your hardware
中文字幕
it's just a finite amount of memory, RAM, that little chip
that I showed on the screen with all the little circuits.
中文字幕
And that has more than 3 bits of memory certainly, but it is finite.
And if we're only using, as a matter of convention, 32 bits
中文字幕
to represent things or 64 bits, maybe if we use doubles or something else
called a long-- a long is a 64-bit integer, whereas an integer is
中文字幕
typically 32 bits.
It seems that, at some point, numbers might overflow
中文字幕
and we're going to actually have some, so to speak,
imprecision-- ergo, integer overflow.
中文字幕
So you can actually see this or defenses against this in the real world.
So this is a screenshot from a game that is common on a few different platforms,
中文字幕
and it's a game that allows you to accumulate coins or points really,
or little Lego pieces.
中文字幕
And if you accumulate these points, you'll notice that eventually,
if you have way too much free time, you can only score so high in this game.
中文字幕
What's the highest score apparently, according
to the screenshot from whoever took this after playing for too many hours?
中文字幕
Wasn't me.
4 million-- no, 4 billion, 4 billion.
中文字幕
Why is that?
Well, it turns out that, if numbers and computers, as I've proposed,
中文字幕
are generally stored using 32 bits.
That kind of invites the question, well, how high can you count with 32 bits?
中文字幕
Well, 32 bits means you have 32 zeros and ones.
The biggest they could be is like 11111, 32 ones.
中文字幕
And if you actually do the math using our little columns and so forth,
it's roughly 4 billion, a little bigger than 4 billion.
中文字幕
So the authors of this Lego game just decided,
you know what, let's just say that the maximum number
中文字幕
of points or coins you can accumulate in this Lego game is 4 billion even.
Why?
中文字幕
It just looks even cleaner than whatever the actual value is.
But why?
中文字幕
How many bits are they using to store your score in this game presumably?
32 bits or 4 bytes, and that's just convention.
中文字幕
Whatever language they programmed this game is,
probably has a data type called an int, and that int by convention
中文字幕
uses 32 bits.
So at some point, they had to decide, we can either use more memory
中文字幕
as you proposed earlier for doubles.
Let's use 64 bits.
中文字幕
Then you can have crazy numbers of hours playing the game
and getting more and more points.
中文字幕
Or we can just say that's enough points to accumulate in the game.
Now that's when you actually anticipate this.
中文字幕
This doesn't always actually happen.
If we go ahead and take a look at some example code--
中文字幕
let me go ahead and open up overflow dot C. In this program
here, you'll see line 8 the slash slash syntax,
中文字幕
and I've had a bunch of these so far.
But I haven't actually mentioned them.
中文字幕
It turns out in C, just in Scratch-- the odds are you didn't notice this little
feature of Scratch--
中文字幕
you can have what are called comments.
A comment is just a note to yourself, to your TF, to your friend,
中文字幕
to your colleague, with whoever whom you're writing code with.
And it's just a note to self to remind yourself of what the code does.
中文字幕
Without this line, I could once, I'm comfortable enough programming,
figure out what these lines of code are doing.
中文字幕
But frankly, that's a waste of time I wrote the code once.
And if I look at it weeks or months later or someone else wrote it,
中文字幕
just tell me what it does.
So a comment in a program is just like a nice summary of a few lines of code,
中文字幕
or it's a summary in English or whatever spoken
language that describes what otherwise a cryptic looking code
中文字幕
might actually be doing.
So you don't have to think too hard about it to understand a program.
中文字幕
So iteratively double i-- iteratively just means loopingly, again and again
and again.
中文字幕
This is funky.
We didn't see this, before but you might guess what it does.
中文字幕
What the star equals do?
It does double.
中文字幕
It's like plus equals adds 1, star equals
doubles if the value on the right is 2.
中文字幕
So this is going to start printing 1 then 2 then 4 and 8 and so forth.
And notice this function.
中文字幕
It's called sleep.
It literally is going to sleep for a second,
中文字幕
and that sleep function has a prototype that someone else wrote in a file
called uni standard dot h.
中文字幕
I only know that by looking it up in the documentation.
But that's a new file just for sleeping.
中文字幕
Make overflow, which is apt here.
And let me go ahead and make the terminal window even bigger
中文字幕
for this one-- dot slash overflow.
OK, it's going.
中文字幕
It's going.
It's going to go faster and faster, so to speak,
中文字幕
because we're adding more and more each time by doubling.
2000, 4000, 8000, 16,000--
中文字幕
it's still going-- 64,000, 65,000.
Now we're into the millions--
中文字幕
2 million, 4, 8, 16 million.
It's getting bigger and bigger, all of these big numbers.
中文字幕
Ooh, interesting.
What just happened?
中文字幕
So it turns out, if you double numbers big enough, you get 0 eventually,
also something you probably weren't taught.
中文字幕
So what actually happened?
Control-C, we'll cancel this.
中文字幕
What happened?
I mean, the program is trying to tell me, even though it's a little cryptic,
中文字幕
signed integer overflow.
Signed just means it went from positive to negative essentially.
中文字幕
So what happened?
What's that?
中文字幕
Yeah, it ran out of bits.
I'm doubling the number again and again and again.
中文字幕
And at some point, we carried the one so to speak and it was a 33rd 1,
therefore past the boundaries of a 32-bit value,
中文字幕
and it just rolled over to apparently a negative because at some point--
and we haven't talked about it--
中文字幕
you can use like the leftmost bit in some sense to say positive or negative.
We've just talked about positive so far.
中文字幕
And then at that point, frankly, the computer
just gave up not really knowing what you intended beyond that.
中文字幕
So if you don't write code to handle this situation
and make sure that your numbers are less than 4 billion before you roll over,
中文字幕
just bugs will happen.
And this might seem contrived here, but this happened not too long ago.
中文字幕
So 1999 was just before a lot of people thought
the world was going to end because of the so-called Y2K bug,
中文字幕
and it really wasn't so much a bug as it was lack of forethought or lack
of features.
中文字幕
What was the Y2K problem in a nutshell?
Someone want to propose?
中文字幕
Even in a non-technical sense, yeah.
Computers couldn't display the number 2000.
中文字幕
Yeah, so let me summarize here.
So if they are only using two digits to display values,
中文字幕
you could confuse the year 2000 with actually the year 1900 because,
long story short, what humans did kind of reasonably decades ago was--
中文字幕
space was expensive.
Computers were expensive.
中文字幕
Memory was not as abundant as it is now with all the cloud
storage and the like.
中文字幕
So you know what?
If it was like 1970, do we really care about 1969, 1968, let alone 1900?
中文字幕
Not really let's just assume we're all in the 1900s
and never show or store one 9.
中文字幕
Let's just store two digits for every year.
So 70 is '70 99 is 1999.
中文字幕
But the problem is the humans ended up running code
that they wrote years ago, decades ago way longer than humans
中文字幕
thought they might why.
Well, it's expensive, it's time consuming to change code,
中文字幕
the code is working.
Why try to break it?
中文字幕
Problem is, too, as people aged in and passed away,
there's fewer and fewer people that even knew the languages in which
中文字幕
those programs were written in.
And so now who's going to even update the software?
中文字幕
So lots of problems were feared, and this really just
boils down to because 1999 might have overflowed to not
中文字幕
zero per se but an implicit 1900.
And indeed, this definitely happened, though not nearly
中文字幕
on the scale as people thought.
But it does happen in even more real terms just a few years ago.
中文字幕
This is a Boeing 787, an actual airplane that
had to be grounded for some amount of time
中文字幕
because it had a programming error.
And its summarized here in an online article.
中文字幕
A 787 airplane that has been powered continuously for 248 days,
it turns out was the warning, can lose all of its electrical power
中文字幕
due to the generator going into fail safe mode.
Why is that?
中文字幕
This condition is caused by a software counter
internal to the generator that will overflow
中文字幕
after 248 days of continuous power.
So translate that.
中文字幕
That just means there's software running in the Boeing's actual 787s.
They were using 32-bit integers.
中文字幕
They were using those integers to store hundredths of seconds.
And at some point if you leave your plane on for 248 days, each of which
中文字幕
has 24 hours, 60 minutes in an hour, 60 seconds in a minute,
and 100 tenths of a seconds or 100 one hundredths of a second in every second,
中文字幕
that product of multiplying things out gets big pretty fast.
And on day 249, planes theoretically would shut down even
中文字幕
in the middle of flight for very real reasons
because a really big number rolls over to zero
中文字幕
and that confused the generator.
And these are actual smart airplane engineers
中文字幕
making these kinds of mistakes because of software,
not anticipating one line of code or some number of lines of code.
中文字幕
Or, as you proposed, why didn't they just use more bits?
And again, these are very real concerns.
中文字幕
So this was thankfully addressed and solved, but not before of course there
was quite the scare there.
中文字幕
So it turns out, in an older game, this was the game of Civilization.
It turns out that one of the characters as whom you can play,
中文字幕
Gandhi, is actually not as peaceful a character in the game
is as you might think.
中文字幕
And let's for context just take a look here for a second.
If we actually take a look at some more binary, this in binary
中文字幕
is what number in decimal?
OK, 1.
中文字幕
And this is 8-bit.
So it's a full byte.
中文字幕
8 bits is a byte--
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
中文字幕
So what do you get if you do a 1 minus--
well, if you subtract 1 from this, you obviously get what?
中文字幕
All zeros.
So 1 minus 1 is just 0.
中文字幕
What if you subtract 2 from this value?
What happens?
中文字幕
This is actually called integer underflow, which is just the opposite,
but there's really not too many options to think about this.
中文字幕
If you only have zeros and ones, you can probably
imagine what the bad scenario is.
中文字幕
If 0000001, if you subtract 1, goes to zeros, and then you do it again,
you now underflow, which just brings you around to the opposite 11111111.
中文字幕
So if you have 8 ones, what value is that if you do the math?
Ones, twos, fours, eight 16s.
中文字幕
It turns out it's 255 if you actually do all the math.
So it turns out that this game Civilization
中文字幕
was using a single byte to represent every character's
level of aggressiveness in the game.
中文字幕
And Gandhi's was, as you would expect, by default
initialized to 1, very non-aggressive.
中文字幕
Unfortunately, in this game of Civilization,
when a player adopts democracy in his or her civilization,
中文字幕
their aggression would be automatically reduced by two.
And so if Gandhi went democratic, his aggression wouldn't go to negative 1.
中文字幕
It looped back around to the ludicrously high figure of 255,
making him as aggressive as a civilization could possibly be.
中文字幕
So less impactful, to be sure, than something like the airplane example,
but these problems are omnipresent.
中文字幕
And if you start to keep an eye out in the popular media
or when there are bugs or hacks or exploits,
中文字幕
it's so often because a programmer has made a mistake in his or her code.
They didn't anticipate a scenario or they made maybe reasonable decisions
中文字幕
years ago, but that eventually proved to be
naive in that we're still running the same code, numbers are getting too big,
中文字幕
their math is wrong.
And so very real things happen.
中文字幕
But what's most important for us is just understanding
how and why those things happen.
中文字幕
And so what will we do in the days ahead?
So the next homework assignment, as with Scratch, will be to program something
中文字幕
but this time in C. You will use an environment
called CS50 lab, which essentially is CS50 sandbox, with which we've
中文字幕
been tinkering today.
But it adds to it the instructions and the specification of the problems
中文字幕
that you'll want to solve.
And it'll hold your hands initially through some of these steps.
中文字幕
You don't need to have written everything down and memorized
everything I typed today, but do feel free in the meantime
中文字幕
to go to the course's website and play with any of those examples.
Among the challenges ahead will be to recreate some snippets of games
中文字幕
from yesteryear, thinking about how things you might have seen growing up
can be translated to actual code.
中文字幕
And undoubtedly, among the first things you'll experience, is frustration.
You'll forget the stupid semi-colon or where does the parentheses go?
中文字幕
And you'll have to look back at code.
But keep in mind, none of that stuff matters.
中文字幕
It's absolutely frustrating initially, but what's most important is the ideas
and, honestly, the sense of gratification
中文字幕
that you, like all of CS50 staff before you,
ultimately feel when actually building and creating something of your own.
中文字幕
Let's call it a day there, and we'll see you next time.